<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss
    xmlns:yandex="http://news.yandex.ru"
    xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
    xmlns:turbo="http://turbo.yandex.ru"
    version="2.0">
<channel>
    <turbo:cms_plugin>C125AEEC6018B4A0EF9BF40E6615DD17</turbo:cms_plugin>
    <title>Exam Notes</title>
    <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress</link>
    <description>Notes for Students</description>
                                <language>en</language>
    <generator>RSS for Yandex Turbo v1.28 (https://wordpress.org/plugins/rss-for-yandex-turbo/)</generator>
                    <item turbo="true">
            <title>Sole Proprietorship : Demerits and Limitations</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/05/sole-proprietorship-demerits/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Sole Proprietorship : Demerits and Limitations</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/05/sole-proprietorship-demerits/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Sole Proprietorship : Demerits and Limitations</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Definition of Sole Proprietorship</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/03/sole-proprietorship/">Sole Proprietorship</a> definition according to Prof Hynes</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sole Proprietorship is that form of business which has a single owner, who has the total responsibility of the business, who runs the business and also bears the risk on the failure of business.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Despite high mortality the sole entrepreneur survives.</strong></p>
<p>In the words of Dr. John A Shubin</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Under the Sole Trader-ship Business, a single man is an organizer; he is the owner and runs the business by his own name.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h2>DISADVANTAGES, DEMERITS OR LIMITATIONS OF SOLE TRADER SHIP (PROPRIETORSHIP)</h2>
<p>Following are the main demerits of this system</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Limited Capital</h4>
<p>The arrangement of capital in sole trader business has to be done by its owner from his private resources, which could be limited to his friends and relatives. Thus, due to limited capital, the business also becomes limited.</li>
<li>
<h4>Limited Management Skills</h4>
<p>The organisation and management of sole trade business is done by its owner, whose mental efficiency and skills are limited up to a certain extent. On this ba-sis the development of business also becomes limited up to that extent.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unlimited Liability</h4>
<p>A sole proprietor has to bear the loss of his business himself, because he is the sole owner of the business. If the losses of business cannot be recovered from the assets of the business then his private property may be utilised to recover the loss.</li>
<li>
<h4>Loss in Absence</h4>
<p>The success of sole proprietorship depends on the supervision of the proprietor. If due to certain reasons, like &#8211; ill health etc., the proprietor remains absent from office or goes out of station, the efficiency of work starts declining, because whole responsibility of work would be on employees, and they would never work at the same level of efficiency.</li>
<li>
<h4>Limited Credit</h4>
<p>The credibility of each person is limited. Since sole proprietorship business belongs to a single person, thus, his credit also is limited up to a certain extent. Thus, he is unable to attain the required amount of loan and other facilities beyond that extent. This restricts the progress of the business.</li>
<li>
<h4>Doubtful Secrecy</h4>
<p>For a sole proprietor business, secrecy in business matters becomes a big problem. Due to secrecy, the money lenders who give money to sole proprietor doubts the financial position of him, and it becomes difficult for him to attain more loans from money lenders.</li>
<li>
<h4>Temporary Existence</h4>
<p>The existence of a sole proprietorship firm is not permanent. When the owner of the business dies, or becomes incapable of carrying on the business due to certain reasons, and there is no heir or successor to his business, the business automatically comes to an end. It is also not necessary that his heir is able to successfully run the business, as he previously did.</li>
<li>
<h4>Limited Business Area</h4>
<p>It is very difficult for a sole proprietor to expand his business after a certain limit. Thus, business of sole proprietor runs in a limited area.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unsuitable for Big Business</h4>
<p>After knowing all the disadvantages it can be said that for big business projects, sole proprietorship system is unsuitable.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/04/sole-proprietorship-merits/"><strong>IS SOLE PROPRIETORSHIP THE BEST</strong></a></p>
<h3>IS SOLE TRADE ALWAYS SMALL?</h3>
<p>It would not be justified to say sole proprietorship is the best, by analysing the above merits. After watching all the points it can be said that &#8220;Sole proprietorship is the best only up to the point, when its size is small, because a single person (its owner) cannot control it when its size increases beyond a limit&#8221;. Thus, sole proprietor business is not always small, but it is the best, in a small size.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Sole Proprietorship : Advantages, Merits and Importance</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/04/sole-proprietorship-merits/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Sole Proprietorship : Advantages, Merits and Importance</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/04/sole-proprietorship-merits/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Sole Proprietorship : Advantages, Merits and Importance</h1>
                    </header>
                                <p><strong>One man&#8217;s business is best in the world, if that one man is big enough to manage everything.</strong></p>
<h2>Meaning of Sole Proprietorship</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/03/sole-proprietorship/">Sole trader-ship</a> (proprietorship) is that form of business organisation whose owner is just one person, who is called the sole trader. This person invests capital in the business, and is <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/08/sole-proprietorship-demerits/">solely responsible for all the profits and losses of the business</a>. The same personals the manager and organizer of the business.</p>
<h3>Advantages, Merits and Importance of Sole Proprietorship</h3>
<p>Following are the merits (or importance) of the sole proprietorship system<br />
<!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Free Selection of Business</h4>
<p>The sole proprietor is free to select his own business. He can choose any business, except those businesses which are restricted by the government.</li>
<li>
<h4>Economical</h4>
<p>The sole trader has to arrange for the capital from his own resources. Thus, he always tries to make best utilization of it, because he knows very well that any loss caused even by a minor mistake, has to be borne by him only. Thus, this system is economical.</li>
<li>
<h4>Easy Commencement</h4>
<p>Sole proprietor business can be easily established because it needs not to fulfil any legal formalities. Thus, it can be established easily.</li>
<li>
<h4>Secrecy</h4>
<p>The secrets of the business are limited to its owner only. Thus, the secrets of sole trader business can be kept secret</li>
<li>
<h4>Quick Decisions</h4>
<p>Sole trader is the whole-sole authority of his business. Any decision relating to the business can be taken quickly by him because he needs not to consult any other person on any issue</li>
<li>
<h4>Full Control</h4>
<p>Since, the sole trader is the whole sole owner of his business; he has full control over his business, and all the factors of production work according to his instruction.</li>
<li>
<h4>Full Share of Profits</h4>
<p>The sole trader has full share of profits. This always inspires him to work with determination to attain maximum profits.</li>
<li>
<h4>Enthusiasm and Devotion</h4>
<p>The sole trader is himself responsible for all the losses of his business. Thus, he woks with higher interest, enthusiasm and efficiency, which increases the probability of maximum profits.</li>
<li>
<h4>Easy to Acquire Loan</h4>
<p>The liability in sole proprietor e business is unlimited. Thus, the proprietor can easily get roan on his r personal credit.</li>
<li>
<h4>Benefit of Patrimonial Goodwill</h4>
<p>The sole trader can take the benefit of goodwill, established by his forefather.</li>
<li>
<h4>Spirit of Self Confidence</h4>
<p>The sole trader can take care of all the activities of his business. Thus, the feeling of confidence, patience and responsibility, develops automatically.</li>
<li>
<h4>Direct Interaction with Workers</h4>
<p>Being the own of the business, he remains in direct contact with the workers, which makes possible the quick rectifications of errors, done by them.</li>
<li>
<h4>Tax Saving</h4>
<p>The sole trader does not come under the schemes of &#8220;<em>Double or Multiple Point Tax System</em>&#8220;, like the joint stock company. And in this way, there is saving of tax in sole proprietorship.</li>
<li>
<h4>Development</h4>
<p>All the activities of sole trade have to be performed by the owner, himself. Thus, the qualities like &#8211; ability of risk bearing and skillful leadership etc. are easily and automatically developed in him.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Sole Proprietorship : Definition and Its Characteristics</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/03/sole-proprietorship/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Sole Proprietorship : Definition and Its Characteristics</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/03/sole-proprietorship/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Sole Proprietorship : Definition and Its Characteristics</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Introduction to Sole Proprietorship</h3>
<p>Sole trader-ship or <em>proprietorship </em>is the oldest form of business in all the countries of the world. Along with the progress of business its form has also been changing. But due to its simplicity, quick formation and easiness, this form is the most popular and in practice in the world.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/04/sole-proprietorship-advantages/"><strong>One man&#8217;s business is best in the world, if that one man is big enough to manage everything.</strong></a></p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h4>Meaning of Sole Proprietorship</h4>
<p>Sole trader-ship (proprietorship) is that form of business organisation whose owner is just one person, who is called the sole trader. This person invests capital in the business, and is <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/08/sole-proprietorship-demerits/">solely responsible for all the profits and losses of the business</a>. The same personals the manager and organizer of the business.</p>
<h2>Definition of Sole Proprietorship</h2>
<p>According to Prof Hynes</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sole Proprietorship is that form of business which has a single owner, who has the total responsibility of the business, who runs the business and also bears the risk on the failure of business.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Despite high mortality the sole entrepreneur survives.</strong></p>
<p>In the words of Dr. John A Shubin</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Under the Sole Trader-ship Business, a single man is an organizer; he is the owner and runs the business by his own name.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>Characteristics of Sole Trader-ship (Proprietorship)</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Sole Ownership</h4>
<p>Single person is the owner in this type a of business. That person is responsible for all the things relating to the business. He himself bears all the risk and organize the whole business. On the closure of business he is personally liable for all gains and losses.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unlimited Liability</h4>
<p>The liability of a sole trader is unlimited. On the occasion of any loss in the business, not only the business assets, but also the private assets of the sole trader (house, shop or land etc.) can be sold for recovery of losses.</li>
<li>
<h4>Limited Work Area</h4>
<p>The work at of a sole proprietor business is limited because the capital acquiring and organisational skills of a person are limited. Thus, the progress of sole proprietorship is limited to the resources of its owner.</li>
<li>
<h4>Sole Right on Capital</h4>
<p>The arrangement of Capital to be invested in the sole trade, has to be done by the proprietor. Thus, he has full right on the capital.</li>
<li>
<h4>Sole Management</h4>
<p>The sole proprietor is himself responsible for the control and management of the business. With the expansion of the business, the proprietor can organize staff for his own convenience, but he himself deemed to be responsible for the work done by the managers.</li>
<li>
<h4>No Legal Fornialities</h4>
<p>To start business of partnership or Joint Stock Company, some legal formalities like registration etc. is required, but the sole proprietor need not fulfill any such formalities before starting his business, and business can be easily started.</li>
<li>
<h4>Free to Select his Business</h4>
<p>The sole proprietor can select any business according to his abilities and will, and can make any changes in his selection of business, when required.</li>
<li>
<h4>Willful Commencement and Closure</h4>
<p>The sole trader can commence or close his business any time he wants. He need not fulfill any legal formalities for these.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Importance and Benefits</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/02/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-importance-and-benefits/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Importance and Benefits</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/02/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-importance-and-benefits/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Importance and Benefits</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>IMPORTANCE OR BENEFITS OF THE LAW OF EQUI-MARGINAL UTILITY</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility/">Law of Equi-Marginal Utility</a> has an important place in economics. Even though it is highly <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-criticism-and-limitation/">criticized</a>, its importance cannot be ignored. This applies in the every field of economics, which is clear from the following<br />
<!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>In the Field of Consumption</h4>
<p>This law is very important in the field of consumption because every consumer wants to get maximum satisfaction from his limited income. Along with those goods which consumers are consuming presently; they also keep goods for future consumption, so that they can get equal utility at both the times.</li>
<li>
<h4>In the Fieid of Production</h4>
<p>Usually, producer has capital in a limited quantity but he wants to get maximum profit from his investment (Capital) and it is possible only when the production cost would be less and production would be more. So, the producer uses the cheap and more production giving means (factors of production), at the place of expensive means, until marginal productivity of both the means become equal. In this way, law of Equi-marginal Utility is also applicable in the field of production.</li>
<li>
<h4>In the Fieldof Exchange</h4>
<p>The main basis of exchange, is this law, because in exchange, goods are purchased and told through money and in every exchange, we compare the utility receiving with utility, giving in return. We keep trying to exchange up to that extent, unless the utility giving become equal, to the utility received. Thus, law equi-marginal Utility is the basis of exchange.</li>
<li>
<h4>In the Field of Distribution</h4>
<p>In the field of distribution, this law is helpful in distributing the remuneration in factors of production. National income is distributed in Land, Labour, Capital and Organisation. Share of factors of production is determined according to their marginal productivity. Hence, the producer uses that particular factor more; the marginal productivity of which is more, than its remuneration.</li>
<li>
<h4>In the Field of Public Finance</h4>
<p>In the field of public finance also, this law has very importance. The Principle of Maxirrtum Social Advantage is also based on the Law of qui marginal Utility Government charges more tax from rich and charges less tax from poor people and spend that income in such a ipisray that the poor can get more benefit in comparison to rich persons.</li>
</ol>
<h3>CONCLUSION</h3>
<p>It is clear from the above analysis that Law of equi-marginal Utility is an important basic law of Economics and it is used at wide level. According to Marshall</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This law is applicable in almost every field of economic research.</p>
</blockquote>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Criticism and Limitation</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-criticism-and-limitation/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Criticism and Limitation</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-criticism-and-limitation/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Criticism and Limitation</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>CRITICISMS, LIMITATIONS OR EXCEPTIONS OF LAW OF EQUI-MARGINAL UTILITY</h2>
<p>Following are the main reasons for the criticism of the <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility/">Law of Equi-marginal utility</a> by H. H. Gossen. Although, it is a basic law of economics and consumers knowingly or unknowingly are compelled, to follow this law. This law is applicable in every field of economic analysis.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Generally Consumers are not Calculative by Nature</h4>
<p>Consumers do not spend their income on the basis of calculations, rather they spend their income, according to their habits.</li>
<li>
<h4>Indivisibility of Goods</h4>
<p>Several commodities, such as &#8211; Scooters, .T.V., Machines etc. cannot be divided into small units. Therefore, the comparison of the utility of these units is not possible and also these cannot be compared with marginal unit of other commodities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Consumers are not Rational</h4>
<p>Generally, man is influenced with customs, traditions,habits and fashion. So, he spends his income unintentionally on the commodities that give less utility. Hence, he is not always rational.</li>
<li>
<h4>Correct Measurement of Utility is not Possible</h4>
<p>Correct measurement of utility is not possible because utility is a mental satisfaction.</li>
<li>
<h4>Utility of Money is not Stable</h4>
<p>Like commodities, the utility of money also keep on decreasing. Moreover, the prices of commodities keep on changing (increases and decreases) whereas, money assumed stable in this law.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Knowledge of Utility</h4>
<p>Generally, consumer does not have any knowledge, about the utility of commodities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Durability of Goods</h4>
<p>We keep on receiving utility in the long run, from durable goods. So, in short term the comparison of marginal utility of these goods, is impossible.</li>
<li>
<h4>Maximum Utility does not mean Maximum Satisfaction</h4>
<p>According to critics, actal utility can be maximised but total satisfaction cannot be maximised, by this law. But in practical life, Utility and Satisfaction both are two separates things and these have no direct relation.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unavailability of Few Goods</h4>
<p>Sometimes, Goods of higher utility are not available in the market and the consumer has to consume the goods of lesser utility, at the place of the goods of higher utility.</li>
<li>
<h4>Supplementary Goods</h4>
<p>Some goods are supplementary to each other and these are used simultaneously in certain proportion. Such as, Car and Petrol. This law is not applicable, in respect of these goods.</li>
</ol>
<h3>CONCLUSION</h3>
<p>In spite of above practical difficulties in the implementation of Law of Equi-marginal Utility, this law cannot be considered mere imagination or unreal. In fact, it is a basic law of economics and consumers knowingly or unknowingly are compelled, to follow this law. <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/02/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-importance-and-benefits/">This law is applicable in every field of economic analysis</a>. According to Professor Chapman</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We are not compelled to distribute our income, according to the Law of Equi-marginal utility as a stone thrown in air is compelled in a sense to fall back on the earth; but as a matey of fact, we do so in a certain rough fashion, became we are reasonable.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/02/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-importance-and-benefits/">The importance of this law are also discussed later</a>.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Definition and Explanation</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Definition and Explanation</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Law of Equi-Marginal Utility : Definition and Explanation</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/02/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-importance-and-benefits/">How is Law of &#8220;Equi-marginal utility&#8221; helpful in maximizing the utility of a consumer?</a></h3>
<h2>INTRODUCTION OF LAW OF EQUI-MARGINAL UTILITY</h2>
<p>We know that wants of every man are unlimited. Wants arise again and again but man has limited means (income) to fulfill his wants and means have , alternative uses. Thus, man always face problem of distribution of limited means of alternative uses, on his wants; so that, he may get maximum satisfaction (or utility). Law of Equi-Marginal Utility presents the solution of this problem. This law states that if a person, wishes to get maximum satisfaction from his income, he should spend his income on different items, in such a way that the utility of last unit of money spent on each commodity, should be equal or almost equal. This law of consumption was propounded by a French Economist, H. H. Gossen in 1854 and it is also known as the <strong>Second Law of Gossen</strong>.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>DIFFERENT NAMES OF THE LAW</h3>
<p>Law of Equi-marginal utility is known with several names, such as; Law of Substitution, Law of Indifference, Law of Proportionality, Law of economy, etc.</p>
<h3>ASSUMPTIONS OF THE LAW</h3>
<p>The assumptions of this law are as follows</p>
<ol>
<li>Man (Consumer) is rational being and his aim is to get maximum satisfaction.</li>
<li>Marginal utility of money remains the same (equal).</li>
<li>Consumer spends his money in small quaritities.</li>
<li>Utility can be measured in the form of money.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Definition of Law of Equi-marginal Utility</h2>
<p>According to Gossen</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It is impossible to gratify all wants to the point of satisfaction. It is necessary, in order to obtain maximum satisfaction, to discontinue the satisfaction of different wants at a point at which their intensity has become equal.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>EXPLANATION OF THE LAW</h3>
<figure><img src="https://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/Gossen-1-1.jpg" /><figcaption>Hermann Heinrich Gossen</figcaption></figure>
<p>Law of Equi-marginal utility has three main basis</p>
<ol>
<li>Wants of human (consumer) are uniimi,ted.</li>
<li>Man has limited means but these means can be used alternatively.</li>
<li>Every person wants to get maximum satisfaction (utility) from his limited means.</li>
</ol>
<p>According to the law of Diminishing Marginal Utility, consuming commodity continuously one by one; consumer gets the utility at diminishing rate from each next unit. So, when the consumer spends, his limited income, on different heads, to get maximum satisfaction, he compares the utility of successive units of different heads and replaces the commodity that gives less utility by the commodity that gives utility and this replacement continues, until the marginal utility becomes equal.</p>
<p>This law is highly <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-criticism-and-limitation/">criticized</a> by some of the economists, but its <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/02/law-of-equi-marginal-utility-importance-and-benefits/">importance</a> is also acknowledged by many of them.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Measurement of Utility : Cardinal and Ordinal Approach</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/utility-measurement/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Measurement of Utility : Cardinal and Ordinal Approach</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2018/01/utility-measurement/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Measurement of Utility : Cardinal and Ordinal Approach</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Measurement of Utility</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/utility/">Utility</a> is a Psychological and Personal Concept. There is a deference of opinion, whether measurement of utility can be done or not. Followings are the two approaches are prevalent in this regard.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h4>DIFFERENCE BETWEEN CARDINAL APPROACH AND ORDINAL APPROACH</h4>
<h3>CARDINAL APPROACH</h3>
<p>The economist Marshal and Pigou etc. have their view that utility can measured in the form of moneys According to them, a person will agree to pay for a commodity; just equal to the utility, which he derives from that commodity. If a person is willing to spend more for a commodity, it means that he gaining more (excessive or surplus) utility from that commodity. In this way, it can be said that price to be given for a commodity is a measurement of that commodity. For example, if a person is ready to pay 10 rupees for a coffee, the utility of that coffee for that person Will be equal to 10 rupees. Hence, it is clear from the above example that according to Prof. Marshall, the utility of a commodity can be expressed through Cardinal Numbers like 1,2,3,4 etc. When we express the utility of a commodity in this manner, it is called Ordinal Utility and this approach is Called <em>Cardinal Approach</em>. In other words, according to this approach, utility can be measured.</p>
<h3>ORDINAL APPROACH</h3>
<p>Contrary to above approach, some economists such as Perito, Ellen, Hicks etc. do not agree with approach of Prof. Marshall and Prof. Pigou. According to these economists, utility cannot be measured. These economists criticized cardinal approach of Marshall, on the basis of following points</p>
<ol>
<li>Utility is a psychological concept, which cannot be measured in the form of money.</li>
<li>Utility remains unstable.</li>
<li>Money is not the correct measurement of utility because the -value of money keeps changing itself.</li>
<li>The amount of money, which we are ready to pay to purchase a commodity, it shows only the estimated utility of the commodity, not the actual utility.</li>
<li>Money is not correct measurement of utility on the following ground also that if a poor man is unable to purchase a cycle, how we can say that there is no utility in cycle for him.</li>
</ol>
<p>Prof. Pigou, who was supporter of Marshall&#8217;s approach earlier; accepted later that only intensity of desire can be measured by money, utility cannot be measured. Due to these difficulties&#8217; Prof. Hicks and other economist have finally accepted that utility cannot be measured and they developed a new method of analysis, <strong>Indifference curve analysis</strong> at the place of <em>Utility analysis</em>, in which there is no need to measure utility. In this method, only Ordinal Numbers 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th (serial order) are given for utility. In this way, the utility of shirt is more or less than that of bread is expressed by these serial numbers. Unit of utility has no meaning in Ordinal Approach. When measurement of utility of commodity is made, numbers are arranged in a serial order of their importance, such as, &#8216;First&#8217;, *Seconds and Third&#8217; etc.. For Example &#8211; three students getting highest numbers in a class are shown in an Ordinal Serial order of &#8216;First&#8217;, &#8216;Second&#8217;, and &#8216;Third&#8217;. When utility is given ordinal numbers, it is called Ordinal Utility and this approach is called <em>Ordinal Approach</em>.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Total Utility &#8211; Mutual Relationship with Marginal Utility</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/total-utility/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Total Utility &#8211; Mutual Relationship with Marginal Utility</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/total-utility/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Total Utility &#8211; Mutual Relationship with Marginal Utility</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Definition</h3>
<p>At a given time the overall utility derived from the consumption of all units of a commodity is called Total Utility.</p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<p>According to Professor Meyors,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Total utility is the sum of <a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/marginal-utility/">marginal utilities</a>, associated with the consumption of successive units.</p>
</blockquote>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Units of Bread</th>
<th>Marginal Utility</th>
<th colspan="2">Total Utility</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>50</td>
<td rowspan="5">Increasing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>120</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>140</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>150</td>
<td>Stable</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>-10</td>
<td>140</td>
<td rowspan="2">Decreasing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>-20</td>
<td>120</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>t is clear from the table that consumption of one unit of bread yields utility equal to 50, While 90 utility is derived from the consumption of second unit. In this way, total 150 utility is derived from the consumption of 5 units of bread.</p>
<h3>Mutual relationship between two type of utilities</h3>
<p>It is dear from above table that</p>
<ol>
<li>From the consumption of each next unit of commodity, marginal utility is derived at decreasing rate and total utility increases.</li>
<li>It increases at decreasing rate.</li>
<li>When marginal utility is zero, it is maximum and positive</li>
<li>Even after getting the maximum satisfaction, if consumption still continues, Negative marginal utility is derived and due to this negative marginal utility, total utility also begin to decrease.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Marginal Utility : Definition and Classification</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/marginal-utility/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Marginal Utility : Definition and Classification</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/marginal-utility/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Marginal Utility : Definition and Classification</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Definition of Marginal Utility</h2>
<p>Marginal Utility is the utility which is derived from the consumption of an additional unit of a commodity. In other words, it is the addition to<a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/total-utility/"> total utility</a>, resulting from adding one unit to the consumption of a commodity.</p>
<p>Example : Ram consumes 6 ice creams at a time. In this case, 6 ice creams will be the marginal unit and utility derived by him from adding one unit to the consumption of a commodity.</p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<p>According to modern economist Prof. Bhatia,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Marginal Utility may also be defined as the addition made to total utility by the increment of the last unit consumed.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>Meaning of Utility</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/utility/">Utility</a> means the power that satisfies any want. It is such an internal quality which is found in all commodities desired by a person. The quality (power or capability) of commodity which satisfies the human want; directly or indirectly is called Utility. Those commodities, which have wants satisfying power are called &#8216;Useful Commodities&#8217;.</p>
<h2>Types of Marginal Utility</h2>
<p>The intensity of want of a commodity decreases due to continuous consumption of its successive units at the same time and a situation also comes, when more units of that commodity are consumed, worthlessness is derived at the place of utility.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Positive Marginal Utility</h4>
<p>Until we get maximum satisfaction by the consumption of a commodity, we feel the want of that commodity again and again. We get some satisfaction by the use of every unit. This type of utility is called Positive Marginal Utility.</li>
<li>
<h4>Zero Marginal Utility</h4>
<p>When we do not get satisfaction from the consumption of next unit of a commodity and there is also no loss if we do not consume that commodity; at that time, the utility of that commodity will be zero for us. It is called Zero Marginal Utility.</li>
<li>
<h4>Negative Marginal Utility</h4>
<p>When disutility occurs from consumption of a commodity, it is called Negative Marginal Utility.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Clarification of Different types of Marginal Utility</h3>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Units of Bread</th>
<th>Marginal Utility</th>
<th>Type of Utility</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>50</td>
<td rowspan="5">Positive</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>Zero</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>-10</td>
<td rowspan="2">Negative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>-20</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>In the above table when a person consumes first unit of bread; he get utility equal to 50 cents. If, he continues the consumption of bread, he get the utility 40 from second unit and 30 from third unit, 20 from fourth unit and 10 from fifth unit and zero from sixth unit. Thus, it is clear that as he increases the number of units of bread; he gets utility at decreasing rate from each next unit. This process of positive utility continues till the consumption of fifth unit of bread, at this point, it becomes 10. Up to this level, the utility is Positive. He gets zero utility from consuming sixth unit of bread and this is the maximum limit of satisfaction.</p>
<p>If even after this limit, he continues the consumption of bread, he will get negative utility from seventh and eighth unit of bread. He will get dissatisfaction at the place of satisfaction.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Utility &#8211; Concept and Characteristics of Utility</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/utility/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Utility &#8211; Concept and Characteristics of Utility</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/utility/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Utility &#8211; Concept and Characteristics of Utility</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Meaning of Utility</h2>
<p><figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/utility-150x150.jpg" /></figure>Utility means the power that satisfies any want. It is such an internal quality; which is found in all commodities desired by a person. The quality (power or capability) of commodity which satisfies the human want; directly or indirectly is called <em>Utility</em>. Those commodities, which have wants satisfying power are called &#8216;<em>Useful Commodities</em>&#8216;.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>Concept of Utility</h3>
<p>Wants satisfying power&#8217; has two meanings</p>
<ul>
<li>Capacity to gain satisfaction</li>
<li>Actual Realised satisfaction</li>
</ul>
<p>Estimated (Assumed) Satisfaction of a particular commodity can be equal to, less or more than, the satisfaction, actually realised by consuming that commodity. Estimated satisfaction for a certain commodity depends up on the intensity of desire of a particular person or depends on desirableness.</p>
<h3>Characteristics of Utility</h3>
<ol>
<li>It is a psychological concept, which can only be felt. It cannot be seen.</li>
<li>It depends on the intensity of wants.</li>
<li>It differs from usefulness. Such as, Cigarette has satisfaction for cigarette smoker, but it is injurious (not useful) to health.</li>
<li>Its concept is indifferent from moral point of view.  Such as &#8211; Wine, in spite of being useful for a wine drinker; it is not considered good for moral point of view.</li>
<li>It is related with Consumable Goods only.</li>
<li>It is different from satisfaction</li>
<li>It does not depend on Actual consumption. It is assumption.</li>
<li>It is measurable.</li>
<li>It can be both positive as well as negative. Up to the point of maximum satisfaction, it is positive and after that negative utility is derived.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Types</h4>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/marginal-utility/">Marginal</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/12/total-utility/">Total</a></li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Economics : Difference Between Micro and Macro</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/11/micro-macro-economics/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Economics : Difference Between Micro and Macro</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/11/micro-macro-economics/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Economics : Difference Between Micro and Macro</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Difference Between Micro and Macro Economics</h2>
<p>Micro and Macro economics, both are absolutely vital and a person is only half educated it he understand the one, while being ignorant of the other.<!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>Using micro approach, the individual units are studied, like, the study of a firm or an industry, whereas, using macro approach, the whole of the economy is studied, like national income, national investment etc.</li>
<li>Under <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/10/micro-economics/">micro economics</a>, a perishable individual, consumer or a firm is studied whereas in macro the imperishable (or undying) society is studied.</li>
<li>Slow changes take place in a society whereas in an individual&#8217;s life, mostly quick changes take place.. On this basis quick changes take place in micro (individual) economics, whereas comparatively slow changes take place in macro (group) economics.</li>
<li>According to Prof. J. K. Mehta, micro economics is like an open economy whereas, macro economics is like a closed economy because knowledge about-an individual person or a firm can be easily gained but a lot of time and problems will be faced in gaining knowledge about the entire society</li>
<li>Sometimes, economic activities are changing from the point of view of an individual (micro) but are stable from the point of view of a group (macro). For example, it may be -possible that them is no change in the population of a country but the size of the families in that country getting bigger or smaller.</li>
</ol>
<h3>CONCLUSION</h3>
<p>Even after the above differences it can be said that individual economic analysis (micro) and group economic analysis (macro) are two methods of the study of economic science. In the view of Prof Samuelson</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There is not really any opposition between micro and macro, both are absolutely vital and a person is only half educated it he understand the one, while being ignorant of the other.</p>
</blockquote>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Macro Economics &#8211; Importance, Limitations and Difficulties</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/11/macro-economics/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Macro Economics &#8211; Importance, Limitations and Difficulties</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/11/macro-economics/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Macro Economics &#8211; Importance, Limitations and Difficulties</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Meaning of Macro Economics</h3>
<p>The word <em>macro </em>means big. Thus, in Macro Economics, either the whole economy is studied or those big units which are related to the economy as a whole.</p>
<h2>Definition</h2>
<p>In the words of Prof. Boulding</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Macro Economics deals not with individual quantities as such but aggregates of these quantities, not with individual incomes but national income, not with individual output but with national output.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thus, macro economics studies the various groups related to the whole economy, like, national savings, national income, national consumption, total employment, total production, etc..<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h4>Historical Background</h4>
<p>In its development, <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/keynesian-theory/">Keynes&#8217; book </a><em>General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money </em>played a significant role. Apart from Kaynes, economists like <strong>Walras, Wicksell, Bohm Bowerk and Fisher</strong> also contributed significantly.</p>
<h2>Importance and Merits of Macro Economics</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Importance in Planning</h4>
<p>Macro economies has played a very important role in determining the policies of the modern planning era. It acts as a pathfinder in the determination of economic policies.</li>
<li>
<h4>Importance in Special Areas</h4>
<p>The fields of international trade, national income, national investment are such areas where only macro approach applies not <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/10/micro-economics/">micro economics</a>.</li>
<li>
<h4>Helpful in Understanding Paradoxes</h4>
<p>It is necessary-to take the help of macro economics in understanding the situation under paradoxes because sometimes conclusions drawn-for individual units are not appropriate from the point of view the whole economy. For example, individual savings is a. blessing, while suppose situation like every person of that country is saving money, will be a curse.</li>
<li>
<h4>Helpful in Monetary Policies</h4>
<p>Many monetary problems, like, inflation and deflation etc. can be analysed with the help of macro approach and controlled by adopting the appropriate monetary policy.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Limitations and Demerits of Macro Economics</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>No importance to Individual Units</h4>
<p>Under macro economics, in comparison to individual units, a group of units is given more importance. But it is not necessary that what is right for individual person, would also right for a group. For example, an individual can withdraw the amount saved in a bank at a time but if all individuals do the same, the banks will have to close down.</li>
<li>
<h4>Difficulty in Measuring Aggregates</h4>
<p>Under macro economics, measurement of aggregates becomes very difficult. The reason is that there are numerous items in a group, which are sometimes not possible to measure separately.</li>
<li>
<h4>Danger in Ignorance of Individual Units</h4>
<p>When we study a group under macro economics, there is always a danger that we may ignore the numerous individual units which form the group.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/11/micro-macro-economics/">How are Micro and Macro Economics different?</a></p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Micro Economics &#8211; Importance, Limitations and Difficulties</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/10/micro-economics/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Micro Economics &#8211; Importance, Limitations and Difficulties</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/10/micro-economics/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Micro Economics &#8211; Importance, Limitations and Difficulties</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Introduction to Micro Economics</h3>
<p>In the present times, the study of economics is done from two viewpoints namely <em>Micro</em> and <em>Macro</em>. From the first viewpoint, the economic problems of various units, like &#8211; individuals, families, firms etc. are studied individually, whereas; from the second viewpoint, the same units of persons, families, firms etc., are studied in a combined form. Micro Economics is concerned with a specific, particular or an individual whereas; Macro Economics is concerned with a <em>group</em>.</p>
<h3>Meaning</h3>
<p>The word <em>micro </em>means very small portion. From this point of view, micro economics is the study of specific economics units of the whole economy. Under this, a commodity, a consumer, a firm or an industry is studied individually.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h2>Definition</h2>
<p>According to Kenneth E. Boulding,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In micro economics, particular firms, particular families, individual prices, wages, incomes, particular industries and specific commodities are studied.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4>Historical Background</h4>
<p>Prof. <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/tag/adam-smith/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adam Smith</a> is called the father of micro economics but its development was done by Prof. <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/tag/alfred-marshall/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alfred Marshall</a> and his companions.</p>
<h2>Importance and Merits of Micro Economics</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Correct knowledge of the nature of individual units</h4>
<p>It makes analytical study of individual units, which helps in understanding the nature of economics.</li>
<li>
<h4>Helpful in the determination of economic policies</h4>
<p>It provides significant contribution in the determination of individual economic policies.</li>
<li>
<h4>Helpful in solving economic problems</h4>
<p>It helps in providing solutions to the economic problems of individual units by studying their economic nature.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Limitations and Demerits of Micro Economics</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Ignore the whole</h4>
<p>It ignores the whole economy and studies only the small parts of the economy. Due to this, it does not represent the correct form of the whole economy.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unsuitable in many areas</h4>
<p>There are many areas of economic analysis, where the use of micro economics is unsuitable. In the fields like, international trade, national income, national savings, nation -investments etc. There is limited use micro economics.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unrealistic assumption</h4>
<p>The assumption that the laws of micro economics are also applicable on macro-economics is not correct because it is not necessary that what is appropriate for an individual concern is also appropriate for the whole economy. For example, by the point of view of an employment, it is good for a person and a country that a person of that country is employed at a high post but if each individual of that country is employed at high posts, then it would become a curse for the murky. This is because if even a small activity of daily life is hindered, it would disturb the whole country, like; lack of sweeper in a country would make that country a dust-bin.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/11/micro-macro-economics/">How are Micro and Macro Economics different?</a></p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Comparison Between The Definition Of Wealth or Economics</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/08/comparison-definition-wealth-economics/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Comparison Between The Definition Of Wealth or Economics</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/08/comparison-definition-wealth-economics/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Comparison Between The Definition Of Wealth or Economics</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Similarities Between The Definition Of Marshall And Robbins</h2>
<p>The following similarities are found in the definitions Of <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/06/economics-marshall-definition/">Prof Marshall</a> and <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/economics-robbins-definition/">Prof Robbins</a><!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>Prof. Marshall used the word &#8216;wealth&#8217;, in his definition, whereas; Prof. Robbins has related Economics with &#8216;limited means&#8217; (or scarcity). Therefore, there is similarity in the views of both because wealth is that object or service, whose supply is limited. Thus, Prof. Robbins limited resource (scarcity) statement, is another form of money.</li>
<li>Both the intellectuals consider Economics as a science. In this way, there is similarity in the views of Marshall and Robbins on this matter.</li>
<li>According to Prof Robbins, the utilization of resources must be done economically, so that production or satisfaction becomes maximum. Marshall has expressed the same view, as &#8216;material welfare&#8217; or &#8216;human welfare&#8217;.</li>
<li>The ancient Economists had considered Economics as the Science of Wealth, which was interpreted as man is for money, instead of that money is for man. In this manner, the main subject matter of Economics was considered, as wealth and not man. Marshall used the word &#8216;Mankind&#8217; and Robbins used words like &#8216;Human Behavior&#8217;, clearly stated that in Economics, man has an important place instead of wealth.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Differences Between The Definition Of Marshall And Robbins</h2>
<p>The definitions of Prof. Marshall and Prof. Robbins have the following dissimilarities</p>
<ol>
<li>Marshall definition is simple and an. ordinary person. can easily understand it. From this point of view, it is practical, but Robbins definition is so much theoretical, that is why, it is very difficult and beyond the understanding power of ordinary people.</li>
<li>According to Prof. Marshall, Economics has a close relation with &#8216;Human Welfare&#8217;, whereas; according to Robbins, Economics is not related to any &#8216;Welfare&#8217; or &#8216;Non-welfare&#8217;.</li>
<li>Marshall presented Economics in the form of both a science and an art, but Robbins accepted it only in the form of a real science.</li>
<li>Marshall has considered Economics as a &#8216;social science&#8217;. According to him, it studies only the activities of social, normal and real persons, whereas; according to Robbins, it studies the both socialistic and sole (aloof), in this way, it is a human science.</li>
<li>Marshall has said that Economics studies only those activities, which are related to wealth and which can be measured in money, whereas; Robbins has said that Economics also studies those activities, which have no relation which money, like &#8211; the study of activities related to &#8216;scarce resources&#8217;.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Which Definition is Superior?</h3>
<p>It is difficult to say which definition between Marshall&#8217;s and Robbins is superior. Actually both definitions are complementary to each other. Marshall&#8217;s definition is easier having a practical view, whereas; Robbins definition has theoretical view point. Both Economists have seen the same thing, from different angles. In Marshall&#8217;s view, wealth is in the form of prime means, whereas; Prof. Robbins has taken in his views, &#8216;scarce resources&#8217;, instead of &#8216;wealth&#8217;. From theoretical point of view, if, Robbins definition is superior, while from practical point of view, Marshall&#8217;s definition is superior.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Criticism Of Robbins Definition</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/08/robbins-definition-criticism/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Criticism Of Robbins Definition</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/08/robbins-definition-criticism/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Criticism Of Robbins Definition</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Criticism Of Robbins Definition</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/economics-robbins-definition/">Robbins definition</a> could be criticized in a way that it does not practically applicable, it provide only a theoretical view.<!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Unnecessary Enlargement of the Scope of Economics</h4>
<p>Robbins&#8217;s definition has unnecessarily widened the scope of economics. According to Robbins, any activity of choosing, whether it is economic or not, comes under the scope of economics. Example &#8211; If a student thinks of choosing between studies and cinema, this activity of decision making will also come under the scope of economics. But critics are of the opinion that uneconomic activities should not be included in economics.</li>
<li>
<h4>Neutrality of Ends</h4>
<p>In Robbins view, it is the duty of the economist to explore and explain and riot to support or criticize. Thus, economics is neutral between ends and the economist is not concerned with, what is right and what is wrong. But this view of Robbins is highly criticized.</li>
<li>
<h4>Based on Theoretical View</h4>
<p>In Robbins view, there is no place for humanity, and human welfare and his definition lacks practicality. Thus, we can only call it a theoretical view. Such economics which cannot be applied in practical life, it does not retain any utility.</li>
<li>
<h4>Applicable only on a Few Countries</h4>
<p>Robbins definition is applicable in only those countries where Barter Exchange System is prevalent. In a barter less economy, Robbins economics will prove a waste because in such an economy, no question arises of scarcity and decision related problems.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unrealistic Assumption</h4>
<p>Robbins believes that each individual does only that activities from which he derives maximum satisfaction. But in practical life, an individual does not always compare the satisfaction he derives from different activities but usually he acts without thinking so much. Thus, this assumption of Robbins is unrealistic.</li>
<li>
<h4>Fixed Economic Laws</h4>
<p>According to Robbins definition, economic laws are as certain fixed, stable and true as the rules of natural sciences. in this context we must not forget that human behavior keeps changing with time and economic laws are concerned with humans only. Thus, economics laws and principles do not remain so stable under variable conditions, as Robbins states.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Robbins Definition Of Economics</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/economics-robbins-definition/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Robbins Definition Of Economics</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/economics-robbins-definition/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Robbins Definition Of Economics</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Introduction Of Robbins</h3>
<figure><img src="https://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/robbins-1-1.jpg" /><figcaption>Prof Lionel Robbins</figcaption></figure>
<p>Robbins definition of Economics challenged Dr.<a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/06/economics-marshall-definition/"> Marshall definition of Economics</a> which was a major improvement over the definition of Adam Smith and other ancient Economists. Before Prof. Lionel Robbins, Prof. Marshall tried to give complete and faultless definition of economics. At that time people started thinking that the Economic Science has completely develop and matured. But in 1932, after the publication of Prof. Robbins&#8217;s book <strong><em>An Essay on the Nature and Significance of Social Science</em></strong>, <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/marshall-definition-criticism/">a controversy roused in the field of Economics</a>. He tried to give economics another shape, apart from material welfare. In the words of Robbins</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Economics is the science which studies human behaviour as a relation between ends and scarce means which have alternative uses.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h2>Characteristics Of Robbins Definition</h2>
<p>Following are the main characteristics of Robbins&#8217; definition</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Unlimited Wants</h4>
<p>According to Prof Robbins definition, human wants are unlimited. On satisfaction of one wants, another want arises immediately.and this sequence continues forever.</li>
<li>
<h4>Scarce Means</h4>
<p>Robbins definition stated that through on one side human needs are unlimited yet on the other side, the means to satisfy these wants, like- time, power, money etc. are also limited. Due to this, many of man&#8217;s needs remain unsatisfied.</li>
<li>
<h4>Alternative Use of Scarce Means</h4>
<p>In Robbins&#8217;s view though the to &#8216;satisfy man&#8217;s needs are scarce, yet he has alternative uses. In other words, he can use every resource in various objectives and activities. For example &#8211; such a resource like land can be use in many ways, such as it can be used for agriculture or for building a house or to established a factory etc.</li>
<li>
<h4>Variation in the Intensity of wants</h4>
<p>Robbins definition states that the intensity of man&#8217;s needs is different. Some wants are more intense than the others. Since our means are limited and all wants cannot be satisfied with the limited means; as a result, we have to select some more intense wants from our unlimited wants and the less intense wants have to be either dropped or postponed to a future date.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Criticism Of Marshall Definition &#8211; Robbins Criticism</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/marshall-definition-criticism/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Criticism Of Marshall Definition &#8211; Robbins Criticism</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/marshall-definition-criticism/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Criticism Of Marshall Definition &#8211; Robbins Criticism</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Criticism Of Marshall Definition</h2>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/Alfred_Marshall-213x300.jpg" /></figure>The <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/06/economics-marshall-definition/">Dr. Marshall definition of Economics</a> is a major improvement over the definition of Adam Smith and other ancient Economists. This definition was recognized between 1890 to 1932 and it seemed that the controversy relating to the definition of Economics had ended. But, a renowned Professor of &#8216;London School of Economics&#8217;, Prof. Leonel Robbins in his book &#8216;An Essay of the Nature and Significance of Social Science&#8217; in 1932 criticized Marshall&#8217;s definition in loud words, which are as follows &#8211;<!--more-->
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Illusion of Anti-Immateriality</h4>
<p>Dr Marshall has restricted the relation of Economics only to the attainment of material resources and its consumption, whereas, Economics also includes the immaterial resources like services of advocates, teachers and other employees. That is the reason Robin said</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Economist who keeps in mind only material study, cannot save themselves from the blame of being biased to one aspect.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Vagueness of Ordinary Business Activity</h4>
<p>The phrase used by Dr. Marshall, &#8220;The activities relating to the ordinary business of life is unclear and vague, because it is not cleat, what activities of man corm under ordinary business and winch activities are outside its area.&#8221; According to Prof. Robbins, though there are several such activities which come under an ordinary business of life, yet are studied in Economics, like &#8211; study of economy at the time of war, conditions of Imperfect Competition, Monopoly, etc.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unclear Economic Activities</h4>
<p>Marshall has divided human activities in two parts, Economic and Non-economic, which is unfair because a similar activity of man can be economic and non-economic also at different times. Like &#8211; sweeping his own house by a servant is a non-economic activity, while sweeping his employer&#8217;s house. becomes an economic activity.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unfair to Relies Economics with Human Welfare</h4>
<p>According to Prof Robbins, Economics has no relation with human welfare, Under this, all kind of activities must be studied, whether it is related to human welfare or not. He gives the following arguments to prove this</p>
<ul>
<li>Production and consumption of alcohol and other intoxicants It not ,beneficial for human welfare, still it is studied in Economics.</li>
<li>Human welfare is not a definite idea; It keeps changing according to time, place and conditions.</li>
<li>Human welfare cannot be measured in quantitative terms.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Economics is not only a Social Science but also Human Science</h4>
<p>Prof. Marshall has restricted the field of Economics, by calling it only a social science. On the contrary, according to Prof. Robbins,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Economics is a human science, whose basic rules apply to an insane, miser, sage or Mahatma in the same mariner, as it applies to all the persons living in a society.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Limited Scope of Economics</h4>
<p>The welfare definitions have restricted the scope of Economics because according to these definitions only material, ordinary and economic activities are studied in Economics. All other activities are outside the scope of Economics.</li>
<li>
<h4>Economics is Neutral between Objectives</h4>
<p>According to Robbins, &#8220;Economics is neutral against objectives. Objectives may be good and also bad, but this has no relation with Economics.&#8221; In his book, Prof. Robbins writes, &#8220;Whatever Economics is concerned with; it is not concerned with the causes of material welfare&#8221;.</li>
<li>
<h4>Economics is a Real Science</h4>
<p>On the basis of the definition of Marshall, Economics has become an ideal science, whereas; according to Robbins, &#8220;<strong>Economics is a real science and not an ideal science</strong>&#8220;.</li>
</ol>
<p>From the above criticisms, it is clear that Marshall&#8217;s definition is narrow and unscientific, and is stuck in the net of immateriality.</p>
<p>Even after the above criticisms, Marshall&#8217;s definition is still a source of inspiration, to the readers. Economists, like &#8211; <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/keynesian-theory/">J.M. Keynes</a>, Hyne and Newman etc. consider Marshall yet as a &#8220;Great knowledgeable Economist&#8221;</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Marshall Definition of Economics</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/06/economics-marshall-definition/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Marshall Definition of Economics</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/06/economics-marshall-definition/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Marshall Definition of Economics</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Economics is a science of choice making.</h2>
<h3>Introduction Of Marshall</h3>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/Alfred_Marshall-213x300.jpg" /><figcaption>Dr. Alfred Marshall</figcaption></figure>
<p>Marshall definition of Economics was first to challenge Adam Smith definition. Dr. Alfred Marshall (Born. 26 July, 1842, Died 13 July 1924) was the first Economist, who denied the wealth related definitions of Adam Smith, which was in vogue for a long time, in his two books published in 1890 named <strong>Principles of Economics</strong> and <strong>Economics of Industry</strong>, and declared them wrong, and defined it as not the study of human welfare. He gave, &#8216;Man&#8217; the first place and Wealth&#8217; as secondary and clarified that wealth is for man and man is not for wealth. Wealth is not the &#8216;End&#8217;, it is only a &#8216;Means&#8217; to attain welfare. He presented the definition of Economics in this manner in his book &#8216;Economics of Industry&#8217;.</p>
<p>However Marshall definition was also <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/marshall-definition-criticism/">criticized</a> later by a renowned Professor of &#8216;London School of Economics&#8217;, Prof. Leonel Robbins in his book &#8216;<a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/07/economics-robbins-definition/">An Essay of the Nature and Significance of Social Science</a>&#8216; in 1932.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h2>Marshall Definition Of Economics</h2>
<p>Economics is the study of human activities in the ordinary course of business. It studies how man attains his income and how he utilizes it. In this way, it studies wealth, on one hand and on the other hand, it is a part of the study of man, which is more important.<br />
According to this definition, it becomes the science of human activities instead of science of wealth. In his second book, &#8216;Principles of Economics&#8217;, Dr. Marshall defined it in these words</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Economics is the study of humans, in relation to the ordinary business of life. It studies that portion of the personal and social activities, which are closely related to the attainment of material resources, related to welfare and its utilization.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>Characteristics Of Marshall&#8217;s Definition</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Greater Emphasis on Human Aspect</h4>
<p>Marshall has given a balanced importance to <em>Means</em> and <em>Ends</em>, through his definition. He has stated in clear words, that it is on one hand is the study of wealth and on the other hand, more important to this is the study of human aspect. In this way, he removed the defect of ignorance of human aspect, in the old views of Adam Smith&#8217;s time, and gave more emphasis to human aspect in clear words.</li>
<li>
<h4>Material Welfare</h4>
<p>Marshall in his definition gave more importance to the means of material gains or material welfare. According to him, it studies, those material resources, on which welfare depends. In this a way, Marshall accepted the material welfare aspect. Other famous economists like &#8211; Pigou, Cannon, Beveridge etc. also supported it.</li>
<li>
<h4>Study of Social, Normal and Real Persons</h4>
<p>According to Marshall, economics studies only social, normal and real persons. The study of persons living outside the society or in forests, who-are unusual, alone and abnormal, is not done in it. The activities of unusual persons like &#8211; an insane, a miser, a saint or Mahatma etc. are said to be outside the area of the subject Matter of economics. According to Marshall, it studies the economic activities of only the social, normal and real persons.</li>
<li>
<h4>Study of the Ordinary Business Activities of Life</h4>
<p>In his definition, Marshall paid emphasis to the <em>Ordinary Business Activities</em>. These &#8216;ordinary business activities&#8217; refers to those economic activities, which are related to the attainment and utilization of wealth. In this manner, Marshall gave a clear place, to human economic activities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Practical Point of View</h4>
<p>Marshall adopted a more practical point of view, in defining economics, He gave equal importance to both theoretical and practical aspects of economic activities, and accepted the scientific and artistic aspects of economics.</li>
<li>
<h4>Simple and Clear Definition</h4>
<p>The definition given by Marshall is very simple and clear. According to him, economics studies the activities of earning and expending wealth by man.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Agricultural Marketing &#8211; Suggestions For Problems The In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/05/agricultural-marketing-suggestions/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Agricultural Marketing &#8211; Suggestions For Problems The In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/05/agricultural-marketing-suggestions/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Agricultural Marketing &#8211; Suggestions For Problems The In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Defects/Problems Of Indian Agricultural Marketing</h3>
<p>Even though India is an agricultural country, still its <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/05/agricultural-marketing-problems/">agricultural marketing has been defective</a>. The Indian farmers are unable to get reasonable price for the products even after their hard work and are fully exploited by the middlemen.<!--more--></p>
<h2>SUGGESTIONS FOR IMPROVEMENT OF AGRICULTURAL MARKETING</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Elimination of Mediators</h4>
<p>The elimination of mediators is necessary from agricultural marketing, because unless the farmer is allowed the facility of direct sales to the customer, he cannot receive a fair price for it. Thus, with the elimination of mediators, ‘consumer grain centers’ should be established where the farmer sells his produce.</li>
<li>
<h4>Use of Standard Weight</h4>
<p>For improving agricultural marketing standard weights are specifically required, these should be manufactured and organised by the government. If, any defect in weights is reported, strict punishment system should be started so that, there should be no fraud in marketing. This would not only improve the marketing system but the fraudulent tendencies of the traders would also be restricted.</li>
<li>
<h4>Loan Facilities</h4>
<p>In villages loans for the farmers are arranged by well-up people, moneylenders etc., who also make a deal of their produce and exploit them on its basis. If, the government establishes banks, cooperative societies or other financial organisations then this problem can be solved. The farmers in the villages should also be encouraged to spend economically and save money so that at the time of need they get money from their savings. By this, the farmers would not sell their produce in a hurry and get full profits out of it.</li>
<li>
<h4>Development of Means of Transport</h4>
<p>The backbone of agricultural marketing is means of transport. Thus, such roads should be constructed in rural areas which remain capable of transportation during all seasons. The tire made bullock carts, diesel or patrol trucks or tractors should be available in rural areas. Similarly, rail and water transport development is also necessary, keeping in view the marketing of agricultural produce, so that the grains and other perishable products can be quickly sent to the market.</li>
<li>
<h4>Publicity of Market Policies</h4>
<p>Sufficient arrangements should be made for the transmission of the authorized prices of agricultural produce and quantity of production etc. so that the facts relating to agricultural marketing can be put before the concerned parties.</li>
<li>
<h4>Training Facilities</h4>
<p>For the improvement of agricultural marketing, it is necessary that arrangements are made for the appropriate training of the employees related to marketing administration. Training with regard to the system of controlled markets etc., is very important for the improvement of agricultural marketing.</li>
<li>
<h4>Regulation of ‘Mandis’</h4>
<p><figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/integrated-scheme-for-agricultural-marketing-300x201.jpg" /></figure><br />
To provide a fair price to the farmers for their produce in the mandis, ‘organised mandis’ should be established by the government, appropriate arrangements should be made in these mandi-markets for weighting, storage, transport etc. and the farmers should also be given regularly powers in it.</li>
<li>
<h4>Market Survey</h4>
<p>The Indian government should establish Marketing and Inspection Directorate for market survey, which collect useful data relating to production, consumption, export, demand price level, standardization, distribution system etc. and publishes them from time to time.</li>
<li>
<h4>Stores Management</h4>
<p>The Indian government has established The All India Storage Corporation realizing the importance of storage. The object of this corporation is to establish stores in villages, cooperative societies are instructed to organize the stores system. For this they are provided additional, technical and financial assistance.</li>
<li>
<h4>Grading and Standardization of Products</h4>
<p>Though the Agricultural Production Act was passed in 1937 for standardization etc. of agricultural products, still no recognizable progress has been made in this direction. For making an effective system of expansion of the activity of gradation and quality control, laboratories should be established. A central laboratory was established in Nagpur and provisional laboratories were established in Madras, Kanpur, Rajkot, Amritsar, Calcutta and Mumbai but these should be situated in small villages and not in big towns.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Agricultural Marketing &#8211; Problems of Agricultural Marketing in India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/05/agricultural-marketing-problems/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Agricultural Marketing &#8211; Problems of Agricultural Marketing in India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/05/agricultural-marketing-problems/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Agricultural Marketing &#8211; Problems of Agricultural Marketing in India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Agricultural Marketing</h2>
<p><em>Agricultural marketing refers to all those processes which relate to taking the agricultural product from the farmers to the consumers. Agricultural marketing includes gathering the agricultural produce, their standardization and grading, their storage, sending them to the market through various middlemen, selling in the market and arranging the required finance etc.</em></p>
<h3>Defects/Problems Of Indian Agricultural Marketing</h3>
<p>Even though India is an agricultural country, still its agricultural marketing has been defective. The Indian farmers are unable to get reasonable price for the products even after their hard work and are fully exploited by the middlemen.<!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Too Many Intermediates</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/fruit_vegetable_market-300x200.jpg" /><figcaption>Fruit &amp; Vegetables Market</figcaption></figure>
<p>The one main defect of the Indian Agricultural marketing is the presence of too many middlemen and exploitation of farmers by them. On one hand these middlemen exploit the farmers by purchasing the produce at lower prices and on the other hand they exploit the customers by demanding higher prices from them. The only aim of a number of commission agents, brokers etc. is to derive a higher income from the middle processes. These middlemen take undue advantage of the poor former on the basis of their financial resources.</li>
<li>
<h4>Defective Weights and Scales</h4>
<p>One of the biggest defects of agricultural marketing arises due to weights and scales. Usually, in rural areas bricks, etc. are used as weights and in urban markets also defective weights are found. Thus, the grain of the farmer is weighed by a heavier weight for their own gain. Most of the traders keep separate weights for purchase and sale of grain.</li>
<li>
<h4>Illiteracy and Lack of Unity among Farmers</h4>
<p>The Indian farmers are illiterate who are easier be fooled by the money lenders, traders, middlemen, due to their simple nature. Similarly, lack of unity among farmers also causes their exploitation because Indian farmers are spread in distant areas in rural places. They are unable to meet with each other and resolve their problems, as a result they do not get a fair price for their produce.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Financial Resources</h4>
<p>In the rural areas there is lack of financial resources, due to which even their emergency requirements are not fulfilled. In such conditions the farmers sell their produce before its ripening. Similarly, some financial facilities, like, installments on loans for pumping-set, tractor, thrasher etc. have to be paid on monthly or quarterly basis due to which they have to sell the product as soon as possible. Thus, as the lack of financial assistance, is a problem for the farmers; so does the receipt of loan also puts them in problem.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Organised Marketing System</h4>
<p>The agricultural marketing is also very defective in India because here organised marketing is not in vogue, like, cooperative societies, government marketing activities, regular markets etc. As a result, the farmer remains entangled In exploitation. Thus, lack of organised marketing system is harmful for the farmers. That is -why; the farmer sells his product personally to different people. The middle take full advantage of the unorganized farmers.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Transport Facilities</h4>
<p>The roads from Villages to cities are usually unmade which are not capable of transport during the rainy season. The bullock carts can take the product only up to a limited area. During lack of transport facilities the farmer is unable to take his produce to the appropriate market and is unable to receive a fair price for his product.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Store Houses</h4>
<p>An important deficiency of Indian agricultural marketing is lack of store houses. Due to lack of this facility the farmer is unable to keep his product safely until it can fetch a fair price, and he is forced to sell his product at a low price. The insufficient and unscientific facilities of shortage which are available, waste large quantities of grains. Approximately 20% to 30% grains are lost due to rats, insects etc. and the farmers have to bear crores of loss due to lack of these facilities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Standardization</h4>
<p>The lack of standardization and grading is clearly visible in the Indian Agricultural marketing, due to which fixing a deal in relation to these products becomes difficult. Due to lack of proper standardization and grading the customers have problem in purchasing the product.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Awareness of the Market</h4>
<p>The Indian farmer has no knowledge about marketing. He believes on information acquired from the businessmen and money lenders of the village. Mostly, the Indian farmers are illiterate so they cannot read the newspaper. Thus, they do not have sufficient knowledge about the market. Now, government transmits the rates of the market on the ratio, which has definitely benefited them.</li>
<li>
<h4>Corrupt Policies of the ‘Mandis’</h4>
<p>If we observe the condition of the mandis, this fact is no more hidden that the middlemen and the traders jointly make fool the simple farmers. The Indian Organizing Society has clarified the following facts relating to the corrupt policies of the mandis</p>
<ul>
<li>The inappropriate marketing system is so deep laden in India that about 5% of the amount is deducted from the farmer’s produce in the name of donations, ‘dharmada’, ‘chanda’ etc.</li>
<li>The farmers are paid low price, as they lack appropriate knowledge about market prices, their fluctuations, government policies etc. Thus, by keeping the rates secret, the farmers are cheated.</li>
<li>Before the sale, large amounts of grains are taken from the farmers as samples. By declaring the product to be of sub standard quality minimum prices are paid for it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Agricultural Labor &#8211; Suggested Remedies Of The Problems of Agricultural Labor In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/agricultural-labor-remedies/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Agricultural Labor &#8211; Suggested Remedies Of The Problems of Agricultural Labor In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/agricultural-labor-remedies/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Agricultural Labor &#8211; Suggested Remedies Of The Problems of Agricultural Labor In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Problems of Agricultural Labor in India</h2>
<p>The Indian agricultural labor spends his days in dirt and mud. He produces food grains for us but remains hungry himself. He feeds our cows but never gets anything but water. He fills our stores with food grains, but begs his own ration for the whole year. He continuously chops woods and fills water for those who have become rich on behalf of his labor. His condition is heart wrenching and Piteous.<!--more--></p>
<h2>Suggested Remedies Of The Problems</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Distribution of Land</h4>
<p><figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/indian-agricuture-problems-300x199.jpg" /></figure>It has always been the effort of the government that whatever additional land is available, it be distributed among the landless. The government has also made efforts to distribute the barren land after making it usable or fertile to theseagricultural labor . It is estimated that till now about more than 10 million agricultural laborers have been provided with land.</li>
<li>
<h4>Industrialization in Villages</h4>
<p>Village <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrialization/">industrialization</a> has been given specific importance during the planning period. The object of this program is to reduce the dependency on agriculture and revive the cottage and small industries in villages.</li>
<li>
<h4>To Spread Education</h4>
<p>To solve the various problems and difficultiesagricultural labor education should be encouraged, so that they can restrict the exploitation of landowners, calculate their correct wages and contribute in the revolutions undergoing in agriculture.</li>
<li>
<h4>Development of Cooperative labor</h4>
<p>To improve the conditions of agricultural labor the expansion of labor cooperative societies is being encouraged, but more development is necessary. In government tenders the labor Cooperative Societies are always given preference.</li>
<li>
<h4>Improvement in Working Conditions</h4>
<p>The working conditions of agricultural laborer should be improved. They should be provided rests and vacations.</li>
<li>
<h4>Regulation of working Hours</h4>
<p>Similar, to the industrial laborers, the working hours of agricultural laborers should also be fixed. Additional wage payment system should be there on working for more than the fixed time.</li>
<li>
<h4>Elimination of slavery</h4>
<p>The Indian constitution has declared Agricultural slavery as crime, so that agricultural laborers are not exploited. Its strict compliance is necessary.</li>
<li>
<h4>Organisations of Agricultural Laborers</h4>
<p>Like the industrial laborers, organisations should also be established for agricultural laborers so that the laborers are able to safeguard their rights. Moreover, labor warfare centers should be established by these organisations at the block levels. At these centers, the entertainment and general education facilities should be available for the laborer.</li>
<li>
<h4>Employment scheme</h4>
<p>This scheme was started in 1971 with a view to provide employment facilities to agricultural laborers. It has been implemented by the government in various forms.</li>
<li>
<h4>Shelter for Landless Laborer</h4>
<p>Science 1971, a scheme to provide shelter to landless laborers is going on. The total expenditure incurred on this program is met by the Central Government.</li>
<li>
<h4>Minimum Wage Act</h4>
<p>The Minimum Wage Act of 1984 has also been implemented on agricultural laborers. In the 14th summit of Indian Labor conference, it was decided that the state government can implement the minimum wages anytime. The minimum wages of agricultural labor in various states like – Uttar Pradesh, West Bengal, Karnataka, etc. has already been fixed.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Agricultural Labor &#8211; Problems of Agricultural Labor In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/agricultural-labor-problems/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Agricultural Labor &#8211; Problems of Agricultural Labor In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/agricultural-labor-problems/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Agricultural Labor &#8211; Problems of Agricultural Labor In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Agricultural Labor</h2>
<p>Agricultural labor is that person who works on another land, does not participate in farm management and its maintenance, and receives money or a portion of the harvest in consideration for his service. He neither has any rights regarding the land, nor does he have to bear any risk regarding the farm. Briefly by agricultural labor we mean’ such laborers who <em><strong>“earn their livelihood by working on agricultural farms.”</strong></em></p>
<h3>Definition</h3>
<p>According to Second Agricultural Labor Investigation society</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Agricultural labor refers to that person who receives more than half of the income from agriculture. The agricultural labor family refers to that family, whose more than half of the income from agriculture.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h2>Problems of Agricultural Labor in India</h2>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/agri_labor-300x220.jpg" /><figcaption>Agricultural Labor</figcaption></figure>
<p>Describing the conditions of Indian agricultural labor P.T.Mayya writes,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Indian laborer spends his days in dirt and mud. He produces food grains for us but remains hungry himself. He feeds our cows but never gets anything but water. He fills our stores with food grains, but begs his own ration for the whole year. He continuously chops woods and fills water for those who have become rich on behalf of his labor. His condition is heart wrenching and Piteous.</p>
</blockquote>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Excess Working Hours</h4>
<p>The working hours of these laborer are not only irregular but also excessive. They have to work since morning to late night. His working hours change with harvest, season and work.</li>
<li>
<h4>Seasonal Employment</h4>
<p>The agricultural labor does not get work for the whole year. According to the Second Agricultural Labor Investigation Society, a Seasonal labor gets an average of 197 days of work in a year. Similarly, child labor gets 204 days and women get 141 days of employment. Thus, their average annual income is very lower.</li>
<li>
<h4>Low Wages</h4>
<p>The wage level of agricultural labors very low as compared to that of industrial labor. It has two reasons</p>
<ul>
<li>increase in landless laborers</li>
<li>lack of non-agricultural areas of work in rural areas.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Agricultural Slavery</h4>
<p>Majority of agricultural laborers are landless and of backward classes. Due to their lower social status they are treated as animals. Big land owners make them work as slaves. They are used as laborers and in return given minimum wages.</li>
<li>
<h4>Indebtedness</h4>
<p>Due to lower income, the indebtedness of agricultural farmers is increasing. They hesitate in negotiating their wages with the land owners in the fear that their services would be terminated. The laborers remain indebted even after working with the land owners for their whole life.</li>
<li>
<h4>Not United</h4>
<p>Since the agricultural laborers are spread in millions of village all over the country they lack unity. Thus, they are unable to negotiate their wages etc. with the land owners by uniting themselves.</li>
<li>
<h4>Exploitation of Child and Women Laborers</h4>
<p>Due to lower income the children and women of agricultural laborers are also forced to work for their livelihood. The child and women laborers are made to work more for livelihood. Thus, exploitation of child labor and woman labor is a major problem in the field of agriculture.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lower Social Status</h4>
<p>Most of the agricultural laborers are of backward classes who have been exploited since centuries. Due to this reason also their social status is lower.</li>
<li>
<h4>Shortage of Other Jobs</h4>
<p>There is shortage of other jobs in villages. Thus, if the crop is destroyed by floods, famines etc., it becomes difficult for the agricultural labor to survive.</li>
<li>
<h4>Housing Problem</h4>
<p>The landless laborers have no private house. They live in cottages, made on the useless land of the landowners with their permission and in its return they have to work without payment, for the landowners. When a number of people live under the same root, the physical, social, moral and religious problem arises.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unemployment due to mechanization</h4>
<p>At the present times, due to increase in the use of machines, <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/">unemployment</a> rate among the illiterate agricultural farmers is increasing, which is a serious problem for them.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Agricultural Productivity &#8211; Suggestions For Problem Of Low Productivity in India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/low-agricultural-productivity-suggestions/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Agricultural Productivity &#8211; Suggestions For Problem Of Low Productivity in India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/low-agricultural-productivity-suggestions/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Agricultural Productivity &#8211; Suggestions For Problem Of Low Productivity in India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>What is Agricultural Productivity?</h2>
<p>Agricultural productivity (<a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/low-agricultural-productivity-india/">Low Agricultural Productivity In India</a>) is measured as the ratio of agricultural outputs to agricultural inputs. While individual products are usually measured by weight, their varying densities make measuring overall agricultural output difficult.<!--more--></p>
<h3>Suggestions For Problem Of Low Productivity in India</h3>
<p>While agricultural production so low in India here are few measures that could be taken to overcome this problem in near future. Following are some suggestions to deal with the problem of low production in India.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Expansion of Credit Facilities</h4>
<p>To increase agricultural productivity, it is essential that the credit facilities be appropriately expanded. This would help the farmers fulfill their short term, medium term and long term financial requirements easily. All efforts should be made to provide credit facility to farmers quickly and economically.</li>
<li>
<h4>Education and Training of Farmer</h4>
<p>Through education and training, the farmers should be encouraged to improve the farming techniques, use scientific methods to increase productivity and enhance their skills. Proper education system would eliminate superstition, conservatism and ignorance among farmers and it would be easier to increase the productivity by the development of these human qualities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Improvement of Irrigation Facilities</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/irrigation-300x204.jpg" /><figcaption>The Narmada Main Canal is the largest irrigation lined canal in the world, supplying water at a capacity of 1,133 cubic meters a second.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Indian agriculture is called a gamble of rains. This condition should quickly end. A network of irrigation facilities should be spread. The small irrigation plans and the wells and tube-wells system should be expanded on a preference basis.</li>
<li>
<h4>Plant Protection Scheme</h4>
<p>Arrangements should be made to protect the plants from insects and diseases. More insecticides should be manufactured and arrangements should be made to increase their use. Development of research work relating to diseases should be done to benefit from these researches.</li>
<li>
<h4>Technical Suggestions</h4>
<p>To increase the agricultural productivity it is necessary to have a technical service system for scientific solution for production problems. Agricultural productivity can be increased on the basis of these technical suggestions.</li>
<li>
<h4>Expansion of Marketing Facilities</h4>
<p>Making the marketing system better and lawful to remove its defects would increase productivity. When the farmers would receive fair price for their labor, then they will perform the production activity and more skillfully.</li>
<li>
<h4>Encouragement to Cooperative Farming</h4>
<p>To increase productivity and make the agricultural system progressive, cooperative farming should be rapidly expanded. Cooperative farming would help the farmer correct the present uneconomical methods of farming.</li>
<li>
<h4>Population control</h4>
<p>Necessary effort should be made in the direction of reducing the pressure of <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/population-problem-solution/">high population</a> on agricultural land.</li>
<li>
<h4>Health Improvement</h4>
<p>Effective efforts should be made in improvement of the health of farmers. System of proper and balanced diet and health facilities should be established. Only the healthy farmers can attain the objective of increasing productivity. Lack of efficiency of unhealthy farmers resulting in low productivity, it can be removed only by improvement in health facilities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Scientific Methods of Cultivation</h4>
<p>Cultivation methods should be improved and the should be scientifically carried out, crops should be properly distributed, techniques based on agricultural research should be adopted. All the activities like ploughing, sowing, irrigation etc. should be properly carried out, then only production can be increased.</li>
<li>
<h4>Proper and Quick Implementation of Land Reforms</h4>
<p>Proper and quick implementation of land reforms should be done, so that the farmers are encouraged to bring some basic improvements. Elimination of mediators and permanent ownership of land to farmers should be done immediately.</li>
<li>
<h4>To Initiate Crop Insurance Scheme</h4>
<p>Implementation of crop insurance Scheme would help in increasing agricultural productivity. By this, the farmers would not worry about the uncertainty of production and their income would become stable, by which they would be able to complete the production activity more sincerely.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Agricultural Productivity &#8211; Problem Of Low Productivity in India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/low-agricultural-productivity-india/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Agricultural Productivity &#8211; Problem Of Low Productivity in India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/low-agricultural-productivity-india/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Agricultural Productivity &#8211; Problem Of Low Productivity in India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Introduction To Agricultural Productivity</h2>
<p>Agricultural productivity is measured as the ratio of agricultural outputs to agricultural inputs. While individual products are usually measured by weight, their varying densities make measuring overall agricultural output difficult.<br />
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/Green_Beds_farmlands_India-300x183.jpg" /></figure></p>
<h3>Causes of Low Agricultural Productivity in India</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Heavy Burden of the Population</h4>
<p>In India, the <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/02/population-explosion-india/">burden of the population</a> is too much on the agricultural land; due to which the agricultural activity cannot be properly controlled. In India about 70% people are dependent on agriculture. The increasing burden of the population on agricultural land, is one of the main reasons for low productivity.</li>
<li>
<h4>Illiteracy, Superstition and Malnutrition</h4>
<p>The agricultural productivity depends much on efficiency,, skill and sincerity of human resources. In India, unfortunately, the human resources are suffering from various deficiencies, the Indian farmer is illiterate and superstitious, their health is also frail. In the environment of superstition and conservatism the backwardness and low productivity of agriculture is natural.</li>
<li>
<h4>Defective Social Organisation of Farmers</h4>
<p>The Indian Social organisation of the farmers has been defective. The casts system and joint family system have not provided that encouragement and power by which they can increase their productivity. Due to cast-ism,proper cooperation of all in the agricultural activity is not possible. The family tensions and differences have very much responsible for minimizing the productivity of the farmer.</li>
<li>
<h4>Traditional Methods of Farming</h4>
<p>In India, fanning is done by traditional methods even today. By using good seeds, fertilizers and modem machinery per hectare production can be increased. But, here the same old seeds and traditional methods of farming are used. For irrigation, the farmer still depends on monsoon. Due to the shortage of,stores, the farmer either sells his harvest in the fields or is forced to sell it at low prices, in the market.</li>
<li>
<h4>Size of Fields</h4>
<p>The average size of the fields in India is between 2 acres to 5 acres, which is too less. The agricultural field is not only less but also dispersed. In some areas the size of the field is so small that they cant even be ploughed easily. Due to the small size of the field, the machines etc. cannot be used on it and the farmers have to expand more labor, time and energy. Even of these circumstances, the land disputes between the farmers make them incur the major part of their income on court cases.</li>
<li>
<h4>Insufficient irrigation Facilities</h4>
<p>One of the major reasons of low agriculture productivity in India, is that the farmers still depend on rain and very few farmers have their own irrigation means. Like before partition the total irrigated area was 24%, but after partition it has fallen to 19%, even though the government has started big and medium irrigation schemes, during the planning period from time to time. Thus, now in the ratio of total land, the irrigated area has increased to 36%. This shows that India requires artificial irrigation methods.</li>
<li>
<h4>Uncertainty of Rain</h4>
<p>From the point of view of both time and result, rain is uncertain. Due to this reason Indian agriculture is called a gamble of rains. Scanty rainfall causes droughts, and heavy rains destroy the crops by floods.</li>
<li>
<h4>Faulty and Tenancy System</h4>
<p>Thogh the <i>“Zamidari System”</i> has ended in India and the Land Development Act has been implemented yet still most of the farmers have not been provided land. Since, they don’t have their own land, they do not work sincerely. Thus, productivity is low.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Good Quality manure</h4>
<p>The number of animals in India is so much that each year 165 crore tons of manure can be produced from their urine and dung. Other wastes and useless articles can produce 8.6 mega tons of manure. But, the valuable manure from cow-dung is dried and burned in case of shortage of wood. Thus, due to lack of good manure productivity decreases.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Finance</h4>
<p>The claims of loans have discouraged the Indian farmer. He lacks funds to buy good quality manure, seeds and machines. He fulfills his financial requirement by taking loans from the moneylender. The moneylender exploits him, taking advantage of his condition. Thus, the farmer unable to invest in agriculture. As a result production falls.</li>
<li>
<h4>Crop Diseases and Animals</h4>
<p>The crops get various diseases like termite, redcoat etc. which destroys the crop. Secondly, the various wild animals like Pigs, Neel-Gaye (wild-cows), etc. damage the standing crop. Thus, production falls.</li>
<li>
<h4>Defective Marketing</h4>
<p>One of the reasons of the backwardness of the Indian farmer is defective marketing system. Due to this defective marketing, the Indian farmer is unable to get a fair price for his produce, and as a result he is discouraged from performing his production activity, skillfully. Due to the defective marketing system,the farmers do not earn sufficient income and are unable to succeed in the agricultural activity.</li>
<li>
<h4>Decline in Fertility</h4>
<p>Decline in fertility is also responsible for lower productivity in India. Continuous agricultural activity on land has activated the Law of Diminishing Returns on it. No effective resolutions have been made to restrict continuity of this law.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Integrated Rural Development Program</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/rural-development/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Integrated Rural Development Program</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/04/rural-development/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Integrated Rural Development Program</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Meaning Of Integrated Rural Development Program</h2>
<p>After independence, many development programs and plans were started in India, like Adult Education Plan, Family Planning and Health Program and programs for the development of rural and, small industries. etc. But, due to the diversity of these plans and the differences in their implementation, areas and objects, there was a lack of mutual integrity and coordination due to which many difficulties and administrative problems arose. Though, the various programs had their own achievements yet due to lack of integrity and coordination the need for a wide and comprehensive rural development program was felt.<!--more--></p>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/rural-development-300x198.jpg" /><figcaption>Agricultural Development will Eradicate Poverty and contribute towards Rural Development</figcaption></figure>
<p>It was realized that the roots of poverty are so deep in rural areas that to eradicate it, a powerful, integrated, wide and comprehensive program is required. For the fulfillment of this requirement an Integrated Rural Development Program was implemented in 1978-79. In the beginning, this program was started in 2300 development blocks, but on 2nd Oct. 1980 it was started in all 5011 blocks of the country.</p>
<h2>Objective Of Integrated Rural Development Program</h2>
<p>The main objective of this program was to bring the very poor families of rural areas, above the poverty line. The major work area of this program is the 30 crore people living in rural areas who are below the poverty line.<br />
This program has the following main objectives</p>
<ol>
<li>To bring the families living below the poverty line, above this line and increasing their incomes.</li>
<li>Increase the employment opportunities of poor people and provide them all kind of help and resources.</li>
<li>More production in agriculture and investing more in small industries and other related works.</li>
</ol>
<p>It is estimated that 60 crore people in the country are below the poverty line of which 50 crores are living in rural areas.</p>
<h2>Progress Of The Integrated Rural Development Program</h2>
<p>In the beginning the housing scheme was started in 2300 blocks and each year 300 more blocks were included in this. But on 2nd Oct, 1980 it was started in all the blocks of the country. Under the Integrated Rural Development Program, each year 600 families are provided help, of which 400 families are related to agriculture and related fields, 100 families to rural and cottage industries, and 100 families, to employment areas. First, each poor family is selected and then an appropriate plan is prepared with their consultation, which is partly carried out with the help of subsidy and partly by bank loan.</p>
<p>The 2/3 of resources required to complete this plan are received from Cooperative Banks or Commercial Banks. The right to accept the plans under Integrated Rural Development Program is given to the state government. The acceptance of the plans of the block is done by the state level coordination committee, which consists of representatives of the Central Rural Development Directorate. This committee meets from time to time and gives directions. Different agencies work at district and block levels. At the district level, a three member committee is formed, which has one economist, one investment planning official and a cottage industry official. The work of this committee is to prepare detailed plans for each block and establish integrity between them.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Poverty Problem In India &#8211; Efforts Of Government To Eradicate Poverty In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/poverty-problem-government-efforts/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Poverty Problem In India &#8211; Efforts Of Government To Eradicate Poverty In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/poverty-problem-government-efforts/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Poverty Problem In India &#8211; Efforts Of Government To Eradicate Poverty In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>The Problem of Poverty in India</h2>
<p>India is recognized as a poor country even after around 70 years of independence. Especially in the Rural Sector of India, the condition is worse. Though during the planning periods the national income of-India and the per ca-pita income has increased, social welfare has increased, literacy level has risen and people have been able to fulfill more and more of their requirements but poverty (and specially Rural Poverty) is still present in its alarming form. We have also discussed about various <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/poverty-problem-india/">Reasons Why India Is Still a Poor Country</a>.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h2>Efforts Of Government To Eradicate Poverty In India</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Employment Opportunities</h4>
<p>For eliminating poverty, the government has made wide efforts to provide employment opportunities. At present the policy of ‘Grain for Work’ has been applied, which is giving employment opportunities to million of villagers.</li>
<li>
<h4>Development of Agriculture</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/NP_Himachal_Pradesh_68_6348260166-300x199.jpg" /><figcaption>Agricultural Development should Eradicate Poverty</figcaption></figure>
<p>The government has done commendable work in relating to the availability of irrigation, research, modern techniques, standard quality seeds and fertilizers for the development of agriculture. For irrigation facilities special river-valley projects are made.</li>
<li>
<h4>Fair Market Price and Transportation</h4>
<p>The farmers get a fair price for their produce , many efforts have been made in this direction. The government has established appropriate market organisations and sources of transportation are developed for this purpose.</li>
<li>
<h4>Encouraging Industrial Development</h4>
<p>The government paid attention to <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrialization/">industrial development</a>. This is supposed to give much encouragement to economic development. Along with this, important steps are being taken for the development of cottage industries. Through this, about 6 crore people have been employed.</li>
<li>
<h4>Family Planning</h4>
<p>The government has encouraged programs for family planning to bring down the birth rate.</li>
<li>
<h4>Chak-bandi</h4>
<p>The government has developed the “chakbandi” system to increase production. Under this several small fields are joined to make a big field. Moreover, cooperative farming is also being developed.</li>
<li>
<h4>Five Year Plans</h4>
<p>The government is making special efforts through the five year plan to eradicate poverty. Under this more and more resources are being provided to the farmers.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Poverty Problem In India &#8211; Reasons Why India Is Still a Poor Country</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/poverty-problem-india/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Poverty Problem In India &#8211; Reasons Why India Is Still a Poor Country</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/poverty-problem-india/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Poverty Problem In India &#8211; Reasons Why India Is Still a Poor Country</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h3>Meaning of Poverty</h3>
<p>Poverty refers to that social condition in which a part of the society is unable to fulfill its basic requirements. When a big portion of the population is deprived of the minimum living standard and survives only on the survival level, then it is said that poverty is widely spread in the population.</p>
<h2>The Problem of Poverty in India</h2>
<p>India is recognized as a poor country even after around 70 years of independence. Especially in the Rural Sector of India, the condition is worse. Though during the planning periods the national income of-India and the per ca-pita income has increased, social welfare has increased, literacy level has risen and people have been able to fulfill more and more of their requirements but poverty (and specially Rural Poverty) is still present in its alarming form.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>CAUSES OF POVERTY IN INDIA</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Lower Growth Rate</h4>
<p>The growth rate of the Indian economy is very low. During the 55 years of the planning period the average growth rate has been 3.5% which has deepened the roots of poverty.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unemployment</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/mumbai-street-kids.jpg" /><figcaption>Unemployment In India</figcaption></figure>
<p>The increasing rate of <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/">unemployment in the country</a> has spread more problem. Due to increasing unemployment, poverty has taken a more serious form. For example, the number of unemployed in the country at the beginning of the first plan was 35 million, which is about 26 crores in 2010.</li>
<li>
<h4>Political Causes</h4>
<p>The long bondage of the country has slowed the pace of the economy. The foreign invaders took no interest in the development of basic industries. The Zami-dari system started in the country which exploited the farmers completely. Their agricultural policies gave birth to landless farmers and their exploitation. Poverty also increased their exploitation.</li>
<li>
<h4>Traditional Production Techniques</h4>
<p>In the fields of agriculture and manufacture, the production techniques are traditional which have lowered the production level due to which poverty has increased.</li>
<li>
<h4>Inflation</h4>
<p>In India inflation has taken an alarming shape. Due to this, people are unable to fulfill the basic requirements of their families. Today 50% of the population of our country is covered under the poor class.</li>
<li>
<h4>Dependency on Agriculture</h4>
<p>Most of the population in India depends on agriculture for their living. Each family has a small amount of land. Everyone live together and live with difficulty on a small land and due to the dependency only on agriculture, the person remains poor.</li>
<li>
<h4>Alcoholism</h4>
<p>In India, poverty has also increased due to alcoholism. Each day, in India million of people are destroying their money and health due to the habits of alcoholism. Thus, alcoholism is one of the reasons of the increasing this problem in India.</li>
<li>
<h4>Belief in Fate</h4>
<p>Most of the population in India give importance to conservative attitude and analyse each aspect on the basis of fate. People become inactive on the thought that it is their fate that is making things happen and live lifelong in the lap of poverty.</li>
<li>
<h4>Adverse Environment and Climate</h4>
<p>On the peaks of Himalayas there is always a snowfall, Rajasthan is also under the same climate in another form. Due to the desert, farming etc. is not possible there and poverty has increased. Thus, the adversity of the environment and the climate has a deep impact on growth of the nation.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Natural Resources</h4>
<p>The places where the land is infertile, there is absence of resources for the production. Coal or iron, minerals etc. are also not available there, people of that place are poor. Due to geographical reasons there are several places in India whose 100% of the population is poor. Like, the land of the hilly areas is not at all fit for agriculture. Moreover, due to lack of resources for agriculture also people are poor.</li>
<li>
<h4>Harm by Insects</h4>
<p>The termites attack, the south Indian drops even today and destroy the crops. Moreover, many kinds of insects and rats destroy the wheat, maize, paddy etc., crops. The grains stored by the traders are also destroyed by these insects and rats. On an estimate, about 15 to, 20% of the crops are destroyed by them. Thus, this is also one of the reasons of Indian poverty.</li>
<li>
<h4>Social Evils</h4>
<p>There are several social evils WI India, like dowry, child marriage, Parda system, etc. which have several bad effects and help in raising poverty.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Industries</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/paper-bag-maker-300x200.jpg" /><figcaption>Paper bag maker and seller, Varanasi India</figcaption></figure>
<p>The industry could not develop properly in India. Due to the lack of industries, poverty can be seen on each side in India.</li>
<li>
<h4>Caste System</h4>
<p>Due to caste system people have to carry on their traditional work, even if, they are unprofitable. That is why, the rich people of olden times did not accept small or low grade jobs and instead preferred to die without food, as a result poverty increased in our country.</li>
<li>
<h4>Traditions</h4>
<p>Everything is related with religion in India. For the sake of their own customs and traditions, the illiterate people spend thousands of rupees, and take loans for their traditions and stay strangulated in poverty.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unbalanced Growth of Industries</h4>
<p>The opportunity of industrial development came after independence but due to the policies of the British rule the cottage industries could not get protection. This gave rise to unemployment and poverty.</li>
<li>
<h4>Natural Calamities</h4>
<p>Indian agriculture is dependent on rains, even today. Sometimes, due to less rainfall drought occurs and sometimes due to heavy rainfall crones of rupees of crop is destroyed. These natural calamities have also been responsible for poverty in India.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Suggestions To Solve Population Problem</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/population-problem-solution/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Suggestions To Solve Population Problem</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/population-problem-solution/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Suggestions To Solve Population Problem</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Population Problem In India</h2>
<p>Dr. Julian Huxley has written in his book</p>
<blockquote>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Huxley-232x300.jpg" /><figcaption>Dr. Julian Huxley</figcaption></figure>
<p>India’s condition in relation to population problem is very troublesome. If, India is unable to find a solution to the problem of population, a big political and soda distortion may arise. But, if, it succeeds it would not only get the lead in Asia but (due to wide market) become the center of attraction of the whole world.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The problem of population can be solved by the economic development of the country. To curb the increase in population following suggestions can be implemented.</p>
<p>Read about <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/02/population-explosion-india/">Population Explosion In India</a> and <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/causes-of-population-explosion-in-india/">Causes of Population Explosion in India</a><br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>Proposed Solutions to Population Problem in India</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Strict Implementation of the Rules of Marriage</h4>
<p>Presently the marriageable age for boys and girls under the law is 21 and 18 years, respectively. This should be strictly followed. The parents forbidding this rule must be punished suitably.</li>
<li>
<h4>Reduce the Birth Rate</h4>
<p>To control the birth rate, it is necessary to propagate birth control devices, educating the people, creating profitable job opportunities for them and increasing the living standard of people by this.</li>
<li>
<h4>Propagating Women’s Education</h4>
<p>According to Dr. Alka Cohosh</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Women’s education is necessary in the direction of curbing the rapid increase in population.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In- this context the knowledge of family planning should be included in the school syllabus for girls at secondary level.</li>
<li>
<h4>Moral Restraint</h4>
<p>The educational organisations should compulsorily provide moral education. Birth rate reduces by moral restraint. Moral restraint includes late marriage, bachelorhood and living in restraint manner etc.</li>
<li>
<h4>Tax Relief and Other Benefits</h4>
<p>To make family planning more popular some tax reliefs and other attractions should be given. Unmarried and childless people must be given tax reliefs.</li>
<li>
<h4>Mobile Hospitals</h4>
<p>The state government should arrange mobile hospitals, which should contain all the medicines relating to family planning and other devices and accessories for distribution.</li>
<li>
<h4>Discourage Large Families</h4>
<p>With the object to discourage large families, higher taxes should be imposed on them and tax rebates be offered to small families.</li>
<li>
<h4>Elimination of Superstitions</h4>
<p>By making the village people more educated, efforts should be made to eliminate their superstitions. Family planning scheme should be approved by the village head or Sar-Panch because on his advice more and more people of the village would follow.</li>
<li>
<h4>Proper Advertising</h4>
<p>For this program, films, songs, speeches, discussions and distribution of advertising material should, be used and the Panchayats and social service organisations must be assisted in this work. People’s attitude will have to be changed for the success of family planning program.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Causes of Population Explosion in India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/population-explosion-causes/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Causes of Population Explosion in India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/population-explosion-causes/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Causes of Population Explosion in India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Population Explosion In India</h2>
<p>The fastest rise in the population of India was during the period of 1951 to 1981, in which the population was from 36 crores in 1951 was reached around to 70 crores in 1981. During this period of 30 years, population increased around 34 crores, which is the fastest rise in the history of population statistics. Death rate has become controlled due to modern health and medical facilities and it has reduced to become 15 persons per thousand whereas; birth rate has not got any significant reduction. That is why; this period from 1951 to 1981 is known in India as the period of <strong>Population Explosion.</strong></p>
<p>Read about <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/02/population-explosion-india/">Effect of Population Explosion on Economic Development of India</a> and <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/?p=158&amp;preview=true">Suggestions To Solve Population Problem</a><br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>Causes of Population Explosion In India</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Hot Climate<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/population-300x169.jpg" /></figure></h4>
<p>One of the reasons of fast rising population in India is its hot climate. Due to hot climate, maturity comes at early age in boys and girls, due to which they give birth to their children at their early age. This is one of the main reasons for population explosion.</li>
<li>
<h4>Child Marriage and Multi Marriage System</h4>
<p>In India the tradition of child marriage and multi-marriage system is prevalent. Marriage of around 80% girls of the country is took place at their young age of between 15 to 20 years. Thus, the result of long married life comes in the farm of excessive childbirth. Tradition of multi-marriage system increases the rotation of childbirth. Apart from it, the increasing tendency of widow marriage, due to the social reforms is also increasing childbirth up to some extent.</li>
<li>
<h4>Religious Superstitions</h4>
<p>Our religious Gurus say that if a Hindu person does not has son, then who will perform the religious ritual in its absence. Due to this, person remains engage in the continuous process of giving birth, one by one, in search of male baby. In the same manner, in Muslims both male and female child is a boon (gift) sent by Allah, prevention of their birth by using any means of family planning is a sin. Due to these reasons, population is continuously increasing.</li>
<li>
<h4>Illiteracy and Unawareness</h4>
<p>In India around 36% males and 61% females are illiterate. Neither they have full knowledge of family planning nor they know about the consequences of excessive childbirth. This is one of the reasons of rising population and the situation of Population Explosion’ is emerged.</li>
<li>
<h4>Poverty</h4>
<p>Due to poverty, population is increased of the poor families of our country. People lives in slum, uses their children as a tool, to earn money, hence they always try to increase the number of children in their families.</li>
<li>
<h4>Birth Rate</h4>
<p>In India the average age for marriage is very low, comparatively other nations of the world. This is also a reason for population explosion.</li>
<li>
<h4>Death Rate</h4>
<p>In India the death rate from the year 1900 to 1910 was around 35 to 50 persons per thousand, which is now reduced to only 7 to 8 persons per thousand. This become ‘possible in the country by good and hygienic food, pure drinking water, facilities of hospitals, good cleanness, medical facilities at affordable rates and control over Malnutrition, Pneumonia, Cholera, Epidemic etc. Along with, child death rate has reduced to 69 per thousand, comparatively around 218 per thousand in between the years 1916 to 1920. Due to this also, the position of Population Explosion occurred.</li>
<li>
<h4>Indifferent towards Family Planning</h4>
<p>Illiterate persons and people living in rural areas are indifferent towards family planning. They feel fear even by the name of ‘Operation’. They are not interested even in the use of simplest and cheapest means of family planning.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Social Security</h4>
<p>Due to lack of social security system in India, every parent seeks. shelter at the time of crises and for their old age, in childbirth. Whether this would be son or daughter. In the fear of death of their child at childhood, they give birth too many children, so that any of them would be support of their old age.</li>
<li>
<h4>Arrival of Refugees</h4>
<p>Population is very much increased due to continuous arrivals of refugees in India. At the time of division of India and. Pakistan in 1947, more than 1 crore refugees came to India. In 1962 at the time of attack of China, a huge number of Tibetan refugees came to India. Similarly, in 1971, more than 1 crore Bangladeshi refugees, came to India and even today this problem is still continued. Apart from this, continuous arrival of Nepalis, is also still continued. More than 5 lakhs Tamil refugees had come to India due to Sri Lankan Tamil problem. All these are responsible for population explosion.</li>
<li>
<h4>Other Causes</h4>
<p>Apart from the above, following are other causes of population explosion<br />
1- Social compulsion of Marriage<br />
2- Lack of means of entertainment<br />
3- Bhagyawati (fateful) view<br />
4- Ambition of big family<br />
5- Betterment in economic position<br />
6- Joint family system, etc.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Population Explosion In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/02/population-explosion-india/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Population Explosion In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/02/population-explosion-india/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Population Explosion In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>The impact of &#8220;Population Explosion&#8221; (Rapid Growing Population) on India’s economic development.</h2>
<h5>Is India over-populated? A critical examination of the present population policy.</h5>
<h3>POPULATION EXPLOSION</h3>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/over_population-300x181.jpg" /><figcaption>Hindu devotees try to board a crowded passenger train to take part in the &#8220;Guru Purnima&#8221; festival in Goverdhan town near the northern Indian city of Mathura July 5, 2009. REUTERS/K. K. Arora (INDIA TRANSPORT SOCIETY RELIGION)</figcaption></figure>
<p>The fastest rise in the population of India was during the period of 1951 to 1981, in which the population was from 36 crores in 1951 was reached around to 70 crores in 1981. During this period of 30 years, population increased around 34 crores, which is the fastest rise in the history of population statistics. Death rate has become controlled due to modern health and medical facilities and it has reduced to become 15 persons per thousand whereas; birth rate has not got any significant reduction. That is why; this period from 1951 to 1981 is known in India as the period of <strong>Population Explosion.</strong></p>
<p>Read about <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/population-problem-solution/">Suggestions To Solve Population Problem</a> and <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/causes-of-population-explosion-in-india/">Causes of Population Explosion in India</a><br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>Population Explosion And Economic Development</h3>
<p>Ordinarily, with an increase in population, production also increases and the number of those people also increases, among whom the total increase in production is distributed. Thus, the ultimate effect of increase in population on the level of production per head, would be indifferent or negative. This would depend on the form of increase in population and its directions. If the increase is in the number of dependents, then in place of production, consumers would increase and ultimately the effect on per head production would be adverse. On the contrary, in case of favorable age constitution of the population, its effect on the economic development would be better.</p>
<h3>EFFECTS OF THE INCREASING POPULATION IN INDIA ON ITS ECONOMIC GROWTH</h3>
<p>The explosive increase in population in India has adversely affected the economic development and economy, which is clear from the following facts</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Lower Growth Rate</h4>
<p>Due to the increasing population, the rate of development has been slow. Whereas; the growth rate of Japan during the previous 10 years has been 15%, while the average growth rate of India has been 4% only.</li>
<li>
<h4>Widespread Poverty</h4>
<p>Due to heavy population the benefit of economic development is almost nil in the country. Though during the last 30 years there has been an increase of 15% in the national income, still the per ca-pita income has increased ‘50% only. About 50% of the population of the country is below the poverty line. Read about <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/03/poverty-problem-india/">Problem of Poverty in India</a></li>
<li>
<h4>High Prices</h4>
<p>Due to higher population we find scarcity everywhere and due to scarcity, the prices are heading towards an increase. The country has scarcity of food-grains, scarcity of employment, scarcity of essentials, scarcity of houses, scarcity of oil etc..</li>
<li>
<h4>Excess Burden on the Economy</h4>
<p>The 1.5 crore of increase in the population each year is increasing the burden on the Indian economy.</li>
<li>
<h4>Problems in Industrialization</h4>
<p>Our country has poverty and unemployment only due to higher population. The level of savings and investments is lower and mechanization is discouraged due to excess human resources. The small and cottage industries are primary. Due to all these reasons rapid industrialization has not become possible. The slow pace of capital formation is also a hurdle in <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrialization/">industrialization in India.</a></li>
<li>
<h4>Expenditure on Population Control</h4>
<p>The explosive increase in population in India has forced expenditure of crores of rupees on population control under planned development. These resources would otherwise have been used in the economic development of the country and the standard of living would have improved.</li>
<li>
<h4>Problem of Unemployment</h4>
<p>The means of employment do not increase at the same rate as the increase in population, as a result the existing <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/">problem of unemployment</a> becomes more dreadful. This is the reason for continuous increase in unemployment in India. At the beginning of the first plan, the numbers of unemployed were 35 millions which increased to 26 crores in 2010.</li>
<li>
<h4>Shortage of Food-gains</h4>
<p>Due to the rapid increase in population, to fulfill the requirements of the population since several years, millions of tons of food-grains has to be imported. This has adversely affected the foreign trade.</li>
<li>
<h4>Problem of the Increasing Number of Dependents</h4>
<p>Rapid increase in population increases the burden of number of dependents. According to the 1961 census 47.3% of the population was dependent which increased today to 71.1%.</li>
<li>
<h4>Problem of Capital Formation</h4>
<p>The increase in income due to the economic development is expended in catering to the needs of the increased population, as a result capital formation cannot be increased and investment rate remains lower.</li>
<li>
<h4>Hinders the Growth of Agriculture and Industry</h4>
<p>Increasing population hinders the quick development of agriculture.<br />
It has two reasons</p>
<ul>
<li>Subdivision of land reduces the area of land per person</li>
<li>The burden of population on agriculture increases.</li>
</ul>
<p>Similarly, the increasing population hinders the growth of industry also. Rapid increase in population decreases the savings and investment rates. During lack of capital, the pace of industrial development is slow.</li>
<li>
<h4>Increase In the Burden of Public Utility Services</h4>
<p>For the rapid increase in population, the government has to incur more on housing, education, health, welfare, law and order and security. Thus, funds for development work fall short.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Suggestions For Unemployment In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/suggestions-unemployment-india/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Suggestions For Unemployment In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/suggestions-unemployment-india/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Suggestions For Unemployment In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Suggestions For Removing Unemployment In India</h2>
<p>This article focus on &#8220;<em>Suggestions For Removing Unemployment In India</em>&#8220;, for reasons of Unemployment In India please refer <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/">here</a>.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>Possible Solutions To Unemployment In India</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Control on Population Growth</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/unemployment-300x199.jpg" /><figcaption>It is disturbing as well as distressing to find that the standard of living of man is still below the desired level and unemployment is on the increase.</figcaption></figure>
<p>To control unemployment appropriate controls on population growth should be made, otherwise on the basis of the present growth rate, India’s population would become more than 125 crores by the year 2015.</li>
<li>
<h4>Development of Non-agricultural Subsidiary Industries</h4>
<p>In India agriculture witnesses seasonal unemployment. Thus, in villages the agriculture related industries must be developed so that the farmer is able to earn something in free time. For this, the subsidiary activities of animal husbandry, poultry farming, gardening, milk business etc. can be developed.</li>
<li>
<h4>Development of Small Industries</h4>
<p>Small and cottage industries must be established, so that people get employment at low capital investment. For this, such small scale industries must be developed which are labor intensive.</li>
<li>
<h4>Full Capacity Utilization</h4>
<p>Many industries in India are working at less than their full capacity. Such industries must be encouraged to utilize their full capacity, so that employment opportunities may be increased in such industries.</li>
<li>
<h4>Exploitation of Natural Resources</h4>
<p>The government should search for such natural resources by which new industries may be established. It is a known fact that natural resources are in abundance in India, that is why, it was named as the<em> “Golden bird”</em>.</li>
<li>
<h4>Increase in Investment</h4>
<p>To increase the. employment opportunities, household savings must be encouraged, so that more capital formation may be done and investment increases. This would assist in the establishment of new industries and employment opportunities would increase.</li>
<li>
<h4>Demand and Supply of Labor</h4>
<p>The demand and supply of labor should be coordinated in various production areas. For this, the future demand and supply of labor should be estimated and arrangements for their training etc. be made accordingly, so that the laborers in excess of the demand may find employment, elsewhere.</li>
<li>
<h4>Establishment of Power Houses in Villages</h4>
<p>About 80% of the population of the country lives in villages. To remove unemployment among the 80% population the “Bhagwati Committee”gave suggestions for the establishment of power houses in villages so that small industries may develop and no work stop in villages at night due to darkness.</li>
<li>
<h4>Suggestions of the Labor Commission</h4>
<p>The <em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">National Labor Commission</span></em> gave the following suggestions for the solution of the problem of unemployment and underemployment</p>
<ul>
<li>Predetermination of a national policy for employment</li>
<li>Formation of All India Manpower Services</li>
<li>Change in the education policy</li>
<li>Rapid industrial development</li>
<li>Survey the human resources of the country</li>
<li>Strengthen the job counselling services</li>
<li>Maintain at least one office at each community Development Division.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Other Suggestions</h4>
<ul>
<li>Start the construction of roads</li>
<li>Provide facilities to construct rural houses</li>
<li>Expansion of small irrigation facilities</li>
<li>Agricultural service centers be established so that the technical people get employment also in villages.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Unemployment In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Unemployment In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Unemployment In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Unemployment In India</h2>
<p>In ordinary language, when a person does not find any work for his livelihood, he is called an unemployed and this problem is called the problem of unemployment. In other words, <span style="color: #216300;">if a person is willing to work and physically fit, and still does not get a job to earn his livelihood, such a condition is called unemployment.</span><br />
<!--more--></p>
<h3>CAUSES OF UNEMPLOYMENT IN INDIA</h3>
<p>No one reason can be held responsible for the widespread unemployment in India but the</p>
<p>following are the main causes of the problem in India</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Rapid Increase in Population</h4>
<figure><img src="https://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/mumbai-street-kids-1-1.jpg" /><figcaption>Unemployment In India</figcaption></figure>
<p>The present increase in population in India has created a imbalance in the demand and supply in the labor market. The increase in techniques, capital formation, natural resources etc. is not at the same rate as the rate of increase in population, due to which the additional people are not getting employment and unemployment is increasing.</li>
<li>
<h4>Uncertainty of Agriculture</h4>
<p>Even after the development of science, agriculture in India is dependent on the mercy of nature. Each year millions of laborers have to lose their jobs due to droughts and floods and other natural calamities due to which uncertainty in agriculture and unemployment arises.</li>
<li>
<h4>Improper Attitude</h4>
<p>One of the main reasons in this country is the want of a job by the educated people. They do not want to start their own production unit. Unemployment has also increased due to this improper attitude.</li>
<li>
<h4>Employment to Women</h4>
<p>During the decade of 1950 to 1960, very few women were working, but nowadays their number and percentage has increased. This has also increased unemployment among men.</li>
<li>
<h4>Wide Gap between Wages and Productivity</h4>
<p>Inflation is continuing in the country due to which prices keep increasing. Affected by this, the laborers demand more wages and incentives due to which the cost and price of commodities increases, but demand decreases. This follows reduced production and thus, increases in unemployment.</li>
<li>
<h4>Defective Planning</h4>
<p>Planning work has been going on in the country since independence, but this planning has been defective. A scholars opine that unemployment has also increased due to this reason.</li>
<li>
<h4>Irrational Mechanization</h4>
<p>The government has intentionally encouraged labor substitution activities, keeping in view development of heavy industries, due to which difficulties in the progress of employment opportunities have arisen. It is definite that labor substitution through irrational mechanization would naturally increase unemployment.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of an Extensive Employment Policy</h4>
<p>India has always lacked an extensive and short term employment policy. It is true that unless a solid employment oriented development policy is not evolved and implemented by a stable government of the country, the solution of the problem of unemployment is difficult. Apart from this, the hurdles in production activities, social environment, social evils, religious superstitions, political instability and industrial unrest are increasing the problem of unemployment.</li>
</ol>
<p>Read about <a href="http://www.rnetian.in/2017/01/26/unemployment-types/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Types Of Unemployment</a></p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Industrial Development &#8211; Suggestions For Industrialization In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrial-development/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Industrial Development &#8211; Suggestions For Industrialization In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrial-development/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Industrial Development &#8211; Suggestions For Industrialization In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Industrial Development In Developing Countries</h2>
<p>In developed countries there are several favorable conditions for Industrial Development, but in poor and developing countries there are several problems in its development. Even after some significant developments in the field of <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrialization/">Industrialization in India</a>, the country is still agricultural country and 38% of the national income and 70% of the population depends on the land.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Suppression of Industrial Disputes</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/labor-300x202.jpg" /><figcaption>A child working in an auto-parts unit, making wheels for automobiles. Poor economic growth, along with staggering food prices and a slowdown in industrial production, leaves the RBI baffled, while civilians live hand-to-mouth and struggle to make ends meet.</figcaption></figure>
<p>It is completely true that a satisfied labor is a valuable wealth of an organisation. A satisfactory and efficient system of arbitration of Industrial disputes is very necessary. Through the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 efforts are made to establish Industrial peace but it is insufficient. Efforts should be made to popularize the Group Discussion method. The policy of worker’s participation in management should be strictly followed. The reasons for the disputes should be analysed impartially and methods should be developed accordingly for their solution.</li>
<li>
<h4>Development of Research and Technology</h4>
<p>In developed countries, continuous research is done on industrial problems and production processes etc. New avenues of development are explored through research on scientific and technical subjects. Now.work has been started on this subject here also.</li>
<li>
<h4>Increase in Power Resources</h4>
<p>India has insufficient power resources. Thus, expansion of power resources and establishment of new units should be done. The government should pay attention to this side to encourage industrial development. Power cuts have to be done from time to time which adversely affects production. Thus, solution of this problem is necessary.</li>
<li>
<h4>Proper Use of Natural Resources</h4>
<p>India has sufficient natural resources but due to their improper use industrial development has not been done. Thus, for industrial development proper use of natural resources is necessary. Those areas should be explored where possibilities of industrial development are more.</li>
<li>
<h4>Establishment of Specialized Institutions</h4>
<p>Much importance has been paid to establishment of specialized organizations and institutions to provide steadiness to industrial development. Various institutions are established in several states for the development of special Industries, but various other organisations are required in relation to this.</li>
<li>
<h4>Efficient System of Industrial Management</h4>
<p>Educated and skilled managers are required to run the industrial organisations properly, who are able to understand the complicated problems of industrialization and solve them quickly.</li>
<li>
<h4>Encourage Capital Formation</h4>
<p>For industrial development funds are very necessary, though India completely lacks it. Thus, savings should be encouraged more for capital formation.</li>
<li>
<h4>Encouragement to Private Sector</h4>
<p>The government should provide more and more facilities to the private sector so that the entrepreneurs come forward to invest more and new industries can be established and old industries are modernized.</li>
<li>
<h4>Earnings in Foreign Exchange</h4>
<p>India lacks funds completely. Thus, to establish Industries in India, foreign investors should be attracted. For this, government should provide them better facilities. In this way, new industries would be established, unemployment would be eliminated and foreign exchange be earned.</li>
<li>
<h4>Rational Taxation Policy</h4>
<p>A proper taxation policy also has an important place in industrial development. Inappropriate taxation, causes problems for industrial organisations, in their development. It is necessary that the needed areas have a liberal taxation policy to motivate them.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Industrialization In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrialization/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Industrialization In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrialization/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Industrialization In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Industrialization In Developing Countries</h2>
<p>In developed countries there are several favorable conditions for industrialization, but in poor and developing countries there are several problems in its development. Even after some significant developments in the field of Industrialization in India, the country is still agricultural country and 38% of the national income and 70% of the population depends on the land.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h4>Causes Of Industrial Backwardness Of India</h4>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Scarcity of Labor</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/labor-300x202.jpg" /><figcaption>A child working in an auto-parts unit.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Even when the density of population is high in India, still in some areas like- West Bengal, Assam etc. there is scarcity of labor for agricultural activities. Apart from this, due to lack of organised labor markets in the country the supply of labor is completely in the hands of contractors and they intentionally create scarcity of labor in factories. Moreover, due to lack of transportation, long distances and also for other reasons the laborers travel less from one place to another. In this way, even after the abundance of labor their supply in factories is less.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Infrastructure Facilities</h4>
<p>In a developing country like- India there is lack of infrastructure facilities. There is also lack of energy resources for the development and proper running of industries. We are fully aware of the usual situations of closure of industrial units due to shortage of power supply. Also due to lack of transportation means, hurdles arise in the way of industrial development.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Capital</h4>
<p>For the industrial development a country requires huge sources of funds. In poor countries the per ca-pita income is not even sufficient to fulfill the basic requirements of people. For establishment of Multi-national industries, huge quantities of funds are required. To make available such large quantity of capital resources does not become possible for a developing country, like India.</li>
<li>
<h4>Industrial Conflicts</h4>
<p>For industrial development, industrial peace is very necessary. But due to lack of proper labor policy and mutual harmony an environment of conflict can be seen. We are very well aware of the conditions of strikes, lock outs, ‘Gherao’, destruction etc. The route to industrial development is blocked by industrial conflicts.</li>
<li>
<h4>Science and Technology</h4>
<p>The pace of scientific and technological development in the developing countries has been slow by which the industrialization could not progress. Without higher level science and technology and resources it becomes difficult to succeed in industrialization. This reason is more responsible for creating hurdles in way to industrialization.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Efficient Managerial System</h4>
<p>Without an efficient managerial system the running of industrial units becomes impossible. The industrial system of today has become very complicated and it can be run only with the help of an efficient managerial system. But, this kind of managerial system seems deficient.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of an Incentive Oriented Long Term Industrial Policy</h4>
<p>For rapid development of industries, a suitable long term industrial policy is required. In India deficiency of such a policy is felt through which industrialization could have been made, progressive. In such a situation hurdles in industrialization are natural.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Specialized Institutions</h4>
<p>It is necessary for the development of industries that specialized institutions be established for solving problems and difficulties related to industrialization. In India, there has been a lack of such institutions which provide technical counselling in the preparation of industrial plans, test its efficiency and provide financial and technical resources for their establishment.</li>
<li>
<h4>Unfavorable Social Environment</h4>
<p>One of the reasons of Industrial backwardness in India is adverse social environment. The systems of cast-ism, joint family, religions superstitions etc. have created such a social environment which has always been a hurdle in the industrial development of the country. As per the rule of inheritance the land is divided into small portions which restrict capital formation. Due to lack of capital industrial development becomes impossible.</li>
<li>
<h4>Policy of Imperial Preference</h4>
<p>The imperial preference policy was also a hurdle in the development of Indian industries under which goods were imported without import tax under the British rule and the Indians preferred imported goods instead of the home production, and they were cheaper also.</li>
<li>
<h4>Policies During the British Rule</h4>
<p>During the British rule the cottage and small industries directly and indirectly were affected adversely. The existing small and cottage industries in the country were lost due to the administrative policies. Foreign rule continued in the country for a long time whose main aim was export of raw material and import of finished goods in the country.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Efficient Technical Experts</h4>
<p>India is technically backward and lacks skilled experts for machineries because there are no appropriate training facilities for technicians. To establish new industries, technical experts have to be called from other countries which is very expensive. Thus, this is also a reason for Industrial backwardness of India.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Contemporary Auditing &#8211; Types Of Audit</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/audit-types/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Contemporary Auditing &#8211; Types Of Audit</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/audit-types/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Contemporary Auditing &#8211; Types Of Audit</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Auditing</h2>
<p>An audit is a systematic and independent examination of books, accounts, statutory records, documents and vouchers of an organization to ascertain how far the financial statements as well as non-financial disclosures present a true and fair view of the concern. It also attempts to ensure that the books of accounts are properly maintained by the concern as required by law.</p>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/social-audit-300x140.jpg" /><figcaption>Social Audit</figcaption></figure>
<p>
<!--more--></p>
<h3>Types of Audits</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Statutory or Compulsory Audits</h4>
<p>Statutory or Compulsory Audits refers to the audits of those organisations, whose audit is compulsory, under the laws applicable in that country. Under Statutory Audit the rules relating to the scope of audit, auditor’s qualifications, his rights, duties and responsibilities etc. are determined by the law, which can be increased by an agreement between the employer of the organisation and the auditor, but cannot be decreased in any situation.<br />
The following organisations mainly come under Statutory or Compulsory Audits</p>
<ol>
<li>Joint Stock Companies</li>
<li>Public Trusts</li>
<li>Reserve Bank and other nationalised Banks</li>
<li>Various Corporations, like Life Insurance Corporation Financial Corporations, etc.</li>
<li>Government Committees</li>
<li>Stock Brokers</li>
<li>Sole Proprietorship and Partnership firms whose Sales exceeding Rs. 20 lakhs or Receipts exceeding Rs. 10 lakhs.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Voluntary or Private Audits</h4>
<p>This is the opposite of Compulsory or Statutory Audit. In this, if the employer wants, then only he can get his accounts audited as per his free will. In this way, there are some private organisations which get their accounts audited privately, as per their free will, these are</p>
<ol>
<li>Sole Proprietor business</li>
<li>Audits of Partnership firms</li>
<li>Other persons like – doctors, lawyers etc.</li>
</ol>
<p>All these are not compulsorily bound by the law to get their accounts audited.</li>
<li>
<h4>Government Audits</h4>
<p>The Central and State governments have established a separate department for investigation of their accounts which is called : <strong>Department of Comptroller Auditor General</strong>. This department investigates and audits the accounts of government and government companies. Its highest official is the <em><strong>Comptroller and Auditor General</strong></em>, and this department presents its report before the government.</li>
<li>
<h4>Interim Audits</h4>
<p>When an audit has to be performed in the middle of the year for some special objectives, it is called Interim or Middle Audit. For example, audits performed at the middle of the year for declaring interim dividend, etc.</li>
<li>
<h4>Periodical, Annual and Final Audits</h4>
<p>Such an audit is done at the end of the year, when all the books of accounts are closed, and final<br />
accounts are prepared. In this audit the auditor checks the accounts of the organisation only once during the year. This is also called Periodical, Annual, Final Audits and also known as Balance Sheet Audits.</li>
<li>
<h4>Internal Audits</h4>
<p>In big business enterprises, when some trustworthy, experienced and honest persons of the organisation under the guidance of an officer check the accounts of the enterprise, such kind of audits are called <em>Internal Audit</em> and the officers who perform this are called <em>Internal Auditors</em>. Internal auditor works as a policeman. As, in the presence of a policeman the ill elements are gripped with fear, similarly, in the presence of internal auditor the employees of the organisation remain alert and do not try to commit fraud or mistakes. In addition, the internal auditor also checks, whether the organisation is following the rules framed for it in all matters or not. He also gives valuable suggestions to the management of the organisation in view of making necessary improvements in the rules and regulation and making other arrangements more effective. By knowing the practical importance of ‘Internal Audit’, today usually all big companies make arrangements for internal audit in their offices. It is worth mentioning that <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/internal-check/"><em>Internal Check</em></a> is not same as Internal Auditing.</li>
<li>
<h4>Cash Audits</h4>
<p>When any business organisation or partnership firm appoints an auditor only to check its cash transactions, such kind of audits are called <em>Cash Audits</em>. While preparing his report, the auditor must mention. in such kind of audits, that it is only a <em>Cash Audits</em>.</li>
<li>
<h4>Continuous Audits</h4>
<p>Under this system, the auditor performs audit all throughout the year at definite and indefinite intervals. Usually under this system, the day on which the auditor and his audit staff visits the businessman, they checks the accounts up to that date and comes back after some days and starts from where they had left last time, up to that day. This sequence of checking goes on during the whole year and at the end of the year audit of only a small period remains, which he completes after the end of the year.<br />
According to W.W. Bigg</p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="color: #339966;">Continuous Audits are that in which the audit staff is continuously busy the year round in checking of accounts.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the following organisations Continuous Audit is more useful and necessary</p>
<ol>
<li>Where immediately at the end of the year Balance Sheet and Profit and Loss Account are needed, Like – Banks, Insurance Companies etc.</li>
<li>Where business transactions and contracts are in large quantity and it is necessary to check these transactions continuously.</li>
<li>Where system of ‘Internal Check’ is not applicable and if it is applicable, it is unsatisfactory.</li>
<li>Where possibilities of irregularities and frauds are more and detailed investigation of accounts is necessary.</li>
<li>Where several times during the year, timely preparation of reports and accounts is compulsory, like – various branch offices which have to send various accounts and statements to their head offices several times during the year.</li>
<li>In big sized companies, like Electricity company, Gas company, Petrol company etc., where for completion of audit the auditor requires several months.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Standard Audits</h4>
<p>In this kind of audits some items are checked in detail in full and other items are checked lightly at a glance only. According to Prof. Ronald A. Irish, “Whenever some chosen specific items have to be fully and deeply audited and the balance has to be seen in overview, this kind of audit is called Standard Audit.</li>
<li>
<h4>Management Audits</h4>
<p>In ordinary language, <em>Management Audits</em> is a voluntary system of the appraisal and evaluation of the — efficiency of the management, to run an organisation. Under this the auditor has to examine all activities concerning each area of the administration of the organisation and give his report on the extent of success of the management in achieving its predetermined objectives, and how its efficiency can be enhanced further.</li>
<li>
<h4>Cost Audit</h4>
<p>Cost Audit refers to the investigation of the cost accounts and certifying them. Under cost audit, it is observed, whether or not the institution has prepared its cost accounts, according to the nature of activities carried on by it. Through cost audit, cost control and quality control both also becomes possible. , In the words of Prof. Smith and Day,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Cost Audit refers to the detailed investigation of the cost accounting system and procedure by which its fairness can be proved, and achievement of the objectives of cost accounting may be assured.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<h4><a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/social-audit/">Social Audit</a></h4>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Financial Audit</h4>
</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Routine Checking &#8211; Merits and Demerits</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/routine-checking-merits-demerits/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Routine Checking &#8211; Merits and Demerits</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/routine-checking-merits-demerits/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Routine Checking &#8211; Merits and Demerits</h1>
                    </header>
                                <p>We have already discussed about purpose and objectives of <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/routine-checking/">Routine Checking</a>. In this article we will go through some merits and demerits of <em>Routine Checking</em>.</p>
<h3>Purpose of Routine Checking</h3>
<ol>
<li>Making totals and sub-totals of primary books of accounts, carrying them forward to the next page, and calculating the balances and their checking.</li>
<li>Checking of the ledger postings derived from the primary books and journal, and to see whether they are properly done or not.</li>
<li>To see the totals of debits and-credits of different accounts and their balances.</li>
<li>To check whether balances of various accounts are properly taken to the Trial Balance, or not.</li>
</ol>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h2>Merits Of Routine Checking</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Mathematical Accuracy</h4>
<p><figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/verified-300x116.jpg" /></figure> The mathematical mistakes of the books of accounts are known from this type of checking, it confirms that the accounts are mathematically accurate.</li>
<li>
<h4>Simplicity</h4>
<p>The work of routine checking is very easy. It can be done even by a person of ordinary abilities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Basis of Final Checking</h4>
<p>It also helps in the checking of Trial Balance and Final Accounts. In fact, it is the basis of checking of Final Accounts, on which basis the auditor prepares his report.</li>
<li>
<h4>Knowledge of Errors and Frauds</h4>
<p>Through this, the errors, frauds and misappropriation of accounts are known.</li>
<li>
<h4>Knowing Errors in Posting</h4>
<p>Generally, the chances of mistake are more in ledger, in accounting work. By routine checking it can be known, whether the work of ledger posting is done properly or not.</li>
<li>
<h4>Tracing out Change in Figures</h4>
<p>Various secret Ticks and Marks are used during the process. If any change is made in figures after the checking, it can be easily traced.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Demerits Of Routine Checking</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Carelessness in Work</h4>
<p>The work of routine checking is not of any specific ability, thus, it is done by junior employees. These junior employees take routine check as a mere formality and finish the work quickly and carelessly, due to which chances of various mistakes remaining undetected are there. In fact, this fault is not of routine check but of the persons doing the work.</li>
<li>
<h4>Errors of Principle remain Undetected</h4>
<p>Persons doing routine checking are not much qualified, thus they do not have full knowledge of the Principles of Accounting. Thus, the errors of principle of accounting remain undetected.</li>
<li>
<h4>Monotonous Work</h4>
<p>Since, the work of routine checking goes on in a continuous process, the employees get bored in their work and they don’t take interest in their work.</li>
<li>
<h4>Cleverly done Frauds remain Undetected</h4>
<p>Small mathematical and other inaccuracies can be known through this technique, but cleverly and intelligently planned big frauds cannot be known.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Routine Checking &#8211; Purpose and Objectives</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/routine-checking/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Routine Checking &#8211; Purpose and Objectives</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/routine-checking/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Routine Checking &#8211; Purpose and Objectives</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Routine Checking</h2>
<p>Whether a business is big or small, the record of its daily transactions is kept in the books of accounts. The daily checking of these books of accounts under audit is called <em>Routine Checking</em>. Usually this work is done by the junior staff of the auditor.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/routine-checking-merits-demerits/">Merits and Demerits of Routine Checking</a> are also discussed in later articles.</p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h3>Purpose of Routine Checking</h3>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/verified-300x116.jpg" /></figure>
<ol>
<li>Making totals and sub-totals of primary books of accounts, carrying them forward to the next page, and calculating the balances and their checking.</li>
<li>Checking of the ledger postings derived from the primary books and journal, and to see whether they are properly done or not.</li>
<li>To see the totals of debits and-credits of different accounts and their balances.</li>
<li>To check whether balances of various accounts are properly taken to the Trial Balance, or not.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Objectives Of Routine Checking</h3>
<p>The routine serves the following objectives</p>
<ol>
<li>To know the mathematical accuracy of the accounts, entered in the primary books of accounts.</li>
<li>To know the regularity of accounting in primary books of accounts.</li>
<li>By making use of distinct Ticks and Marks to know that no changes are made in figures after the check.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Ticks And Marks Used In Routine Checking</h2>
<p>While doing routine checking, some signs of different colors are used. These are called Ticks or Check Marks. The main points related to this are</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Precautions</h4>
<p>The following precautions must be taken while using these marks</p>
<ol>
<li>Mark should be small and clear.</li>
<li>Marks should not be of the same color in which accounts are written.</li>
<li>Different colors of marks must be used for different activities.</li>
<li>Marks must be changed each year.</li>
<li>The meanings of marks must be kept secret.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Place of Ticks and Marks</h4>
<p>The place of making the mark must be decided beforehand because along with the colors, types of marks, the place of its use are also very important. Usually for verifying the postings in accounts, mark is made on the left side of the amount. On checking the voucher with the amount, mark is made on the right side. On verifying the total, mark is made below the total etc.</li>
<li>
<h4>Importance of Ticks and Marks</h4>
<p>The Ticks and Marks have great importance in verification. Prof. Emerson while expressing the importance of Ticks &amp; Marks has written that during audit, Ticks and Marks must be kept in mind, in the same way as while walking, we keep track of the road in mind, while talking we keep words in mind and while shopping pocket kept in mind. In all these situations, a little carelessness creates various problems.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Internal Check</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/internal-check/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Internal Check</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/internal-check/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Internal Check</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Meaning Of Internal Check</h2>
<p>Internal check system is a part of the internal control system of the business. This is also called <em>Internal Block</em>. Each trader wants that he should be able to control the internal activities of his business, in such a manner that he can get maximum profits and the. chances of mistakes, fraud, etc., are could be minimum. The system of internal check is one such arrangement, in which the activities of employees are divided in such a manner that the work of one employee is independently checked by the other employee. Unless all employees of the organisation are become united, the chances of fraud etc., is not there.</p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/internal-check-300x202.jpg" /><figcaption>Internal Check</figcaption></figure>
<p>For example – Suppose a customer presents a cheque of ₹1000 to the bank for payment. If all the works of checking the cheque, its investigation, its entry in books of accounts and payment of that cheque are done by a single bank employee, then he can by increasing a zero in ₹1000, make it ₹10000 in the bank books, give payment of ₹1000 only to the customer and can keep himself inappropriately the balance of ₹9000.</p>
<p>If the work of encashment of cheques is divided among three employees, one shall investigate the cheque, and make entries in the books of accounts. Second employee shall check this entry and send it to the third employee making cheque payments. The third employee shall make payment to the customer. In this system a single work is divided among three persons, and the work of first employee is automatically (without any special efforts) checked by the second employee, and the third employee shall make the payment of ₹1000 written in the cheque. In such a case, misappropriation cannot happen, unless all three employees unite.</p>
<h4>Definition</h4>
<p>According to Spicer and Pegler</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The internal check is such a system of management of a business, in which the work which is to be done by the employees is divided by the organisation in such a manner, that no employee can do the written accounting work of a transaction from the beginning to the end, and the work of each employee is also surely and independently checked by another employee, so that without any joint and pre-planned efforts of all employees, the happening of mistakes and frauds becomes impossible, and if any mistake occurs, it is immediately detected at the time of accounting, by another employee.</p>
</blockquote>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Social Audit</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/social-audit/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Social Audit</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/social-audit/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Social Audit</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Social Audit</h2>
<p>The evaluation of the social responsibilities of an industry, company or firm is defined as <em>Social Audit</em>. In practice it can be called the appraisal of the activities of the social responsibilities of an organisation. Every industry runs in the society, for the society, thus the aim of any industry is not only to earn maximum profits, but it has some responsibilities towards the society in which it exists. Through this type of audit, the auditor examines as to what extent the industry is carrying out its responsibilities.</p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h3>Liabilities and Objectives Of Social Audit</h3>
<p>Following are the main liabilities or objectives of social audit</p>
<ol>
<li>To increase the employment opportunities along with the development and expansion of industries.</li>
<li>Engaging in the welfare activities for the workers along with paying them proper wages.</li>
<li>Establishing new industries in economically backward areas.</li>
<li>Responsibility of maintaining a good environment inside the industry and quick completion of the work.</li>
<li>Responsibility of providing quality products to the customers.</li>
<li>Maintaining a healthy social environment in the industry and related areas.</li>
<li>Responsibility of timely compliance of several governmental duties like paying taxes on time, etc.</li>
<li>Responsibility of providing fair return to investors.</li>
<li>Providing better conditions’of work to laborers.</li>
<li>Developing good relations between the labor and management.</li>
<li>Continuous efforts toward employee development.</li>
<li>Continuous efforts towards the development of industries.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Scope Of Social Audit</h4>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/social-audit-300x140.jpg" /></figure>
<p>The scope of this type of audit is very wide, but the problem arises in determining the analysis and limits of those welfare activities. Only after the analysis and determination of limits of these services, the scope of social audit can be determined, and the auditor can analyse those activities which the industry performs for the society.<br />
In this way, it is clear that the responsibility of social audit is to attain social objectives. The attainment of this object is possible only when the auditor presents his unbiased report after its examination, as to what extent the industry has carried out its responsibilities, and whether there is any deficiency in carrying out there responsibilities, the reasons behind it and the method of solving them.</p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Verification Parameters</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/verification-parameters/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Verification Parameters</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/verification-parameters/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Verification Parameters</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Verification Of Assets</h2>
<p>For verification of any assets the auditor has to mainly check some general points, which are almost similar for all kinds of assets, still according to the name of the asset, the auditor verifies them in the following manner</p>
<p>The main parameters to verify the value of an asset are</p>
<ul>
<li>Debtors</li>
<li>Goodwill</li>
<li>Trade Mark</li>
<li>Land and Buildings</li>
</ul>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h5>Debtors</h5>
<p>The auditor should verify this asset carefully because it- might be that full amount has been received from a debtor, but the whole amount is not shown as a receipt and some portion of that amount is shown as discount to debtor and that amount of discount has been fraudulently stolen by the firm by not giving this discount to debtors. This may also be possible that cash may be received from debtor but it is not deposited in his account and theft, and the debt of that person (debtor) is shown as a Bad Debt and written off from Profit and Loss account. The auditor shall verify this asset in the following manner.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h6>Attaining the List</h6>
<p>The auditor shall attain a certified list of total debtors of the firm, from a responsible officer. He shall also attain the necessary documents and receipts of debtors relating to total amount of bad debts.</li>
<li>
<h6>Communication with the Debtors</h6>
<p>If the auditor considers it necessary, he shall communicate with the debtors independently and confirm whether. The amount remaining in balance at the end of the year is also according to their books or not.</li>
<li>
<h6>Checking Bad Debts and Discount to Debtors</h6>
<p>The auditor should see that discount to debtors is given as per the rules and which officer is authorised to give, this rebate. He should also see whether on each discount, the signature of that officer is present or not. Similarly, if for any loan it seems that it is not recoverable and it is written as a Bad debt, the auditor should also check that the officer who has written it, in Bad Debts account was authorised to do so, or not, because it is possible that after showing it as a Bad Debt, the loan was recovered from the debtor and distributed between the officer and the debtor, fraudulently.</li>
<li>
<h6>Checking of Securities</h6>
<p>If any cash loan is given by the organisation by taking some security, then such securities should also be checked.</li>
<li>
<h6>Presentation in the Balance Sheet</h6>
<p>The auditor should see whether any special law applies on that organisation, or not. If any special law applies then he should see that according to that law, how the debtors should be shown in the Balance Sheet. As according to the Companies Act, it is compulsory for the company to show its loans under the following heads</p>
<ul>
<li>Loans which are considered receivable and for which the company is fully secured.</li>
<li>Loans which are considered receivable but in relation to which the company does not have any other security other than the personal security of the debtor.</li>
<li>Loans which are considered Bad and Doubtful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>If no special law applies on the organisation, the auditor shall see that debtors are shown in a manner as shown in other ordinary business organisations.<br />
An important case relating to showing of debtors in the Balance Sheet, is London &amp; General Bank case. In this case, the auditor of London &amp; General Bank Ltd. was held responsible for breach of duty because he did not reveal this fact to the shareholders of the bank in his report that he has shown various loans as asset (debtors) in the Balance Sheet and interest earned on them also shown in the Profit &amp; Loss account as a profit, whereas; fact was this that the chances of recovery of these loans were almost nil, though the auditor was quite aware of this fact.</p>
<h5>Goodwill</h5>
<p>Goodwill is an intangible asset. If it is separated from business then it has no value. Its value depends on the increase and decrease of the profits of the business. If there is any additional profit in any business then the goodwill of the business is considered big.<br />
Goodwill is a separate asset from other assets of the business, its valuation also cannot be done like other assets-of the business because neither it depreciates, nor it requires reconstruction and repairs, etc., or it needs to be replaced.<br />
Goodwill is valued in an organisation in the following two cases</p>
<ul>
<li>While purchasing a running business, in such a case, the Purchase Price of goodwill is known by deducting net assets from the Purchase Price, i.e., (Goodwill = Purchasing Price — Net Asset). For example, if a running business is purchased for Rs. 100000 and the Purchase Price of the assets of the organisation is Rs. 80000, then the goodwill of that organisation will be, 100000 — 80000 = Rs. 20000.</li>
<li>When a new partner is taken in a partnership or any old partner separates from the business, then a goodwill account is opened, at that time.</li>
</ul>
<p>In both the above cases the following method is adopted for the Verification of Goodwill</p>
<ol>
<li>On purchase of goodwill, the auditor must study the contract with the vendor (seller of goodwill) and see that it is shown at the proper value in the books of accounts or not.</li>
<li>If goodwill arises with admission of a new partner in the business or on separation, then the auditor must see the Partnership Deed.</li>
<li>In the Balance Sheet goodwill must be shown at Cost Price.</li>
<li>Sometimes goodwill is written off, and re-opened due to some reasons. If this is done, then the auditor must study the copy of resolution passed by the directors.</li>
<li>Even after complete investigations, if the auditor is not satisfied with the amount of goodwill, then he should state this clearly in his, report.</li>
</ol>
<h5>Trade Mark</h5>
<p>When a product is registered with a specific symbol so that no other producer is permitted by the law to use that symbol. That product and its manufacturer are also identified by that symbol.<br />
For trade mark, the auditor has to perform the following steps</p>
<ol>
<li>If any organisation or its branches has more than one trademarks, the auditor must obtain a list of all trademarks which should contain the details of serial number, date, duration, fees etc.</li>
<li>If trade mark is obtained by paying some amount to another person, the investigation of this payment must be made by the payment receipt, received from him.</li>
<li>If trade mark is such that it is registered for the first time, then the fees paid for registration must be verified from the receipt of the payment made.</li>
<li>If the trade mark is renewed, then the amount paid in renewal should be checked by the receipt which is received against that payment.</li>
<li>The auditor must see the period of trade mark from the Registration certificate attained. The period of a trade mark is usually not more than 14 years. Thus, he should see that during this period, provision for depreciation is provided on trade mark or not. The rate of depreciation should be such that by the time of the expiry of the period of trade mark, it should be fully written off.</li>
</ol>
<h5>Land And Building<figure><img src="https://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/building-1-1.jpeg" /></figure></h5>
<ol>
<li>If building is purchased, its verification must be done on the basis of the contract.</li>
<li>If building is constructed on contract, it must be verified by the certificates of contractors and experts.</li>
<li>If building is constructed by the employees of the organisation only, then the certificate of the responsible officer must be obtained.</li>
<li>Building must be shown in the Balance Sheet, after deducting appropriate depreciation on it.</li>
<li>The existence of the building should be seen by the auditor himself.</li>
<li>Building must be shown at cost price only. The auditor must see that no profits earned by the organisation, are fraudulently included in this amount.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Verification Of Assets</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/verification/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Verification Of Assets</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/verification/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Verification Of Assets</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h4>Meaning Of Verification</h4>
<p>It is the duty of the auditor that he specifically writes in his report whether the financial position of the organisation represented in the Balance Sheet is proper or not. He must make sure that all the assets shown in the Balance Sheet are actually present with the organisation or not, the organisation has valued them properly or not, they are free from all kinds of mortgages etc. or not. Similarly he has &#8216;to make sure about all liabilities also. In this way the auditor evaluates the assets and liabilities of the organisation and verifies them, and this work of the auditor is called <em>Verification</em>.</p>
<p>Read about <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/verification-parameters/">Verification Parameters</a></p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<p>It is clear that verification of assets is such a process by which the auditor certifies that the assets shown in the Balance Sheet are correct. Explaining the complete objective of verification J.R. Batliboi Boy has said that</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Auditor should satisfy himself that the assets are actually present on the date of Balance Sheet and they are free of any charge or mortgage and their valuation is done in proper manner.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/verified-300x116.jpg" /></figure>The auditor must take all kinds of care in relation to assets. He should check all documents of title, receipts etc. related to the assets. Mostly these documents of title are with the trader but if they are with some other person like banks etc., then they should be attained from them. He should not show any kind of relaxation in this. In relation to verification of assets, the position of an auditor is specified in a court case that for verification of assets, the auditor should take care of the following points</p>
<ol>
<li>All the assets are included in the Balance Sheet of the organisation and are shown clearly.</li>
<li>Assets are valued properly</li>
<li>On the date of preparation of Balance Sheet the assets were physically present with the organisation.</li>
<li>All the assets were in possession of the organisation and were free from any charge or mortgage.</li>
<li>Assets were owned by the organisation and not by anyone else.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Objectives Of Verification</h4>
<p>The main objective of verification is to check the following<br />
points</p>
<ol>
<li>Whether all assets and liabilities are mathematically accurate or not.</li>
<li>All assets are properly accounted for, as per the rules of the organisation and legal provisions, or not</li>
<li>All the assets shown in the Balance Sheet are actually present or not, and at the time of preparation of Balance Sheet they were present with the organisation, or not.</li>
<li>Any such change.is made in an asset which is not shown in the Balance Sheet. In other words, assets are shown keeping in view all the related provisions, or not.</li>
<li>Whether fictitious Assets are written off adequately, or not.</li>
<li>Valuation of assets and liabilities is done according to the accounting principles or not and valuation is correct according to the previous year, or not.</li>
<li>No fraud or irregularities occurred in relation to the assets and liabilities of the organisation.</li>
<li>All the assets and liabilities of the organisation are shown or not and none is hidden.</li>
<li>Assets shown in the Balance Sheet are actually present or not and they are owned by the organisation or not. It might be that some assets are not in the possession of the organisation, like &#8211; on taking a loan from bank, the assets or stock of the organisation is kept in the goodwill of the bank. But in such a case, the organisation has legal right over such asset, and it is considered the property of the organisation.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Green Revolution In India &#8211; Criticism Of Green Revolution</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/criticism-green-revolution/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Green Revolution In India &#8211; Criticism Of Green Revolution</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/criticism-green-revolution/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Green Revolution In India &#8211; Criticism Of Green Revolution</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>An Introduction to Green Revolution</h2>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/norman_borlaug-300x200.jpg" /><figcaption>American agronomist, Dr Norman Borlaug</figcaption></figure>
<p>The Green Revolution was started in India by then Prime Minister Late Shri Lal Bahadur Shastri, who gave the slogan of <strong>“Jai Jawan, Jai Kisan”</strong>, according to which, to make the country powerful from security point of, view, is the responsibility of the soldiers, while making it self sufficient in the field of food grains, is the responsibility of the farmers.<br />
<!--more--><br />
American agronomist, &#8220;Father of the Green Revolution&#8221; and Nobel laureate, Dr Norman Borlaug (left) advising a farmer on wheat development programs during his visit to Bombay on March 14, 1971.</p>
<h3>Criticism, Shortcomings And Failure Of Green Revolution In India</h3>
<p>Some critics are of the view that Green revolution has not been very successful in India. It has benefited only some limited farmers. Due to the preference given to some areas, regional inequalities have arisen. Use of excessive fertilizers has made the land useless. It has been criticized on the basis of the following facts.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Increase in Unemployment</h4>
<p>In the rural areas due to extensive agricultural programs, mechanization has been rapid, which has increased unemployment. It is inappropriate for countries like India, where unemployment is already a problem. In this way <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/">unemployment is increasing in rural areas</a>.</li>
<li>
<h4>More Dependence on Fertilizers</h4>
<p>In this agricultural policy, use of fertilizers is given more importance than irrigation, which is not appropriate because in the absence of irrigation, fertilizers have no use. Due to this reason, the fertility of land has decreased in some areas.</li>
<li>
<h4>Economic Inequalities</h4>
<p>The benefit of Green revolution has been received mainly by the prosper farmers. The poor farmers have not benefited from this policy. It has enhanced the economic inequalities.</li>
<li>
<h4>Regional Inequalities</h4>
<p>Under the Green Revolution movement, the implementation of agricultural resources was aimed only in naturally favorable areas, due to which some areas developed and some places were not given any attention. This increased regional difficulties. The prosper areas became more prosper and the backward became more backward.</li>
<li>
<h4>Benefited only a Few Crops</h4>
<p>Green revolution has been successful only on a few crops, specially wheat, rice, maize, jwar and baajra. No work has been done for other crops. Specially relating to crops like cotton or sugarcane etc..</li>
<li>
<h4>Difficulty in Storage</h4>
<p>The progress of agriculture has given rise to an additional problem of storage. At present, the storage capacity of our country is 2.5 crore tons, which is not sufficient with regard to production.</li>
<li>
<h4>Lack of Experience</h4>
<p>Due to unavailability of scientifically developed seeds in India, farmers have been lacking experience experience about them. What effect these modem resources would have on Indian conditions, is not known certainly. Working without experience is like walking without knowing the path, where possibility of going in the wrong direction is more.</li>
<li>
<h4>Difficulties in the Use of Modern Techniques</h4>
<p>Most of the Indian farmers have small lands, hence they have problems in using the modern equipment designed for big lands. In this way, these farmers have remained in acquitted from the benefits of green revolution.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Suggestions For Success of Green Revolution</h3>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/green-revolution-300x225.jpg" /><figcaption>Green Revolution</figcaption></figure>
<ol>
<li>The small farmers should be provided credit facilities at lower interest rates than the big farmers.</li>
<li>The modern techniques should be made profitable for small farmers.</li>
<li>The land development programs should be made effective and activated on a large scale.</li>
<li>The marketing system of agriculture should be improved.</li>
<li>To solve the problem of unemployment due to increased use of instruments and machines the small and cottage industries should be rapidly developed.</li>
<li>The labor intensive techniques should be given preference.</li>
<li>Improved variety of seeds should be developed.</li>
<li>Crop insurance should be started on a large scale for farmers.</li>
<li>The education, research and expansion services should be developed in villages</li>
<li>Irrigation facilities should be expanded.</li>
<li>Landless laborers and farmers should be united.</li>
<li>Programs for plant protection should be expanded.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Green Revolution In India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/green-revolution/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Green Revolution In India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/green-revolution/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Green Revolution In India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>An Introduction To Green Revolution In India</h2>
<p>The Green Revolution was started in India by then Prime Minister Late Shri Lal Bahadur Shastri, who gave the slogan of “Jai Jawan, Jai Kisan”, according to which, to make the country powerful from security point of view, is the responsibility of the soldiers, while making it self sufficient in the field of food grains, is the responsibility of the farmers.<br />
<!--more--></p>
<h2>ACHIEVEMENTS OF GREEN REVOLUTION</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Increase in Production Per Hectare</h4>
<p>By Green revolution the productivity of agricultural land has increased by new agricultural implements. The per hectare production in the country has increased.</p>
<p><figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/green-revolution-300x225.jpg" /><figcaption>Green Revolution : Increased agricultural Production in India</figcaption></figure>
</li>
<li>
<h4>Self Dependence</h4>
<p>The use of developed and modern agricultural implements is given more importance under Green revolution, which has made sufficient increase in the agricultural produce of the country. In 1970-71, the food-grains production was 8 crore tons which increased to about 95 crore tons today. The credit of huge increase in food-grains production in such less time goes to Green revolution. The production of commercial crops like cotton, jute, oil-seeds etc. has also increased as expected.</li>
<li>
<h4>Commercialization of Agriculture</h4>
<p>Till now, agriculture was supposed to be a means of livelihood in the country. Due to the Green revolution, productivity per hectare has increased.Agriculture no longer remains a means of livelihood but now farming is done also for profit making. In this way, the process of its development has increased naturally.</li>
<li>
<h4>Use of Fertilizers</h4>
<p>Now each such farmer of the village has started using chemical fertilizers, who feared its use.</li>
<li>
<h4>Irrigation Facilities in Wider Areas</h4>
<p>Due to expansion of small irrigation plans under the Green revolution, the total irrigated area has increased.</li>
<li>
<h4>Change in Attitudes</h4>
<p>The old farmers always remained dependent on fate.but the results of Green revolution have changed the attitude of farmers. Now he has started believing in Karma than fate.</li>
<li>
<h4>Reduction in Imports and Export Promotion</h4>
<p>By Green revolution, on one hand food-grains etc. are now produced in the country, by which on one hand exports have increased and on the other hand imports have reduced. This has encouraged import substitution.</li>
<li>
<h4>Use of Insecticides</h4>
<p>After the Green revolution, there has been sufficient increase in the use of insecticides.</li>
<li>
<h4>Multiple Crop Program</h4>
<p>The aim of multiple crop program in the Green revolution was to produce more than one crop during,the year and increase production. This plan was first implemented in 1967-68. For this, at present 80 schemes has been running, in which experiments and exhibitions of growing two or three crops are done.</li>
<li>
<h4>Rural Electrification</h4>
<p>Under the Green revolution, the rural electrification Program has been implemented for raising the standard of rural life and providing electricity for agricultural purposes. At the time of implementation of the first plan, electricity was available only in 3000 villages, but now in almost 70% of the villages of the entire country have electricity. To provide funds for supply of electricity in the villages, the Rural Electrification Corporation are also established.</p>
<p><figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/NTPC_Ramagundam-1-300x133.jpg" /><figcaption>Rural Electrification In India</figcaption></figure>
</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Keynesian Theory of Employment</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/keynesian-theory/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Keynesian Theory of Employment</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/12/keynesian-theory/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Keynesian Theory of Employment</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>Introduction to Keynesian Theory of Employment</h2>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Keynes-300x225.jpg" /><figcaption>John Maynard Keynes</figcaption></figure>
<p>Keynesian Theory was given by Keynes when in his volume “<em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money</span></em>” had not only criticized the <strong>Classical Theory of Employment</strong>, but had also analyzed those factors that affect the employment and production level of an economy. Most of the modern economists agree with the concept of Keynes. The Keynesian Theory of Employment is a produce of the world-wide depression of 1931-36. Due to this depression, unemployment spread in all independent capitalist economies. Keynes analyzed that situation of unemployment and tried to find the reason and solution to that problem.<!--more--><br />
During that time, the theories of British economist John Maynard Keynes—of deficit-based, government stimulus spending and strong regulation of markets—dominated economic policy and thought.</p>
<h2>Explanation of the Theory of Employment</h2>
<p><em>“Classical theory of Employment”</em>, but had also analyzed those factors that affect the employment and production level of an economy. Most of the modern economists agree with the concept of Keynes. The Keynesian Theory of Employment is a produce of the world-wide depression of 1931-36. Due to this depression, unemployment spread in all independent capitalist economies. Keynes analyzed that situation of unemployment and tried to find the reason and solution to that problem.</p>
<p>According to this theory, since the demand for goods and services is not so much that the total actual resources may be utilized, unemployment arises. In the words of Keynes,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The deficiency in effective demand, stops the increase in employment to reach the full employment level.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>On an increase in the effective demand of the consumers, the resources are utilized in large quantities, and the level of employment rises. When people start demanding another product in place of a product temporarily, unemployment would increase due to fall in total demand, it shall be of irregular nature. Actually, a permanent fall in demand occurs, when instead of making expenditure on consumer goods, people try to save most part of their incomes. A deficiency in demand for goods and services in one sector of the society in not compensated by an increase in demand for goods and services in another sector, and total demand declines. Thus, if the desire to save from their particular income is more than the desire for substitution expenditure have become a reverse relationship, demand and employment increases i.e., when the desire to save, among people is lesser than the substitution expenditure in the society, demand and employment increases.</p>
<p>In Keynes view, the level of employment of any country depends on its effective demand. Effective demand depends on total supply of production and the total demand. The total supply of a production depends on total investment and total consumption. The amount of consumption is affected by the tendency for consumption, and the size of national income. As the income of a person increases, his tendency to consume comparatively reduces. On the other hand, it depends on the amount of investment, rate of interest, and mostly on the marginal efficiency of capital. In the money market, the demand for capital shall be more even during the period of high rates of interest, if in view of the investors, capital is more efficient. The marginal efficiency of capital depends on the substitution cost and the anticipated profits.</p>
<h2>Reasons of Spreading of Unemployment</h2>
<p>According to Keynes, the three main reasons of spreading of unemployment are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Lack of effective demand</li>
<li>Deficiency of outlay on consumption</li>
<li>Deficiency of investment</li>
</ol>
<p>Read about <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/unemployment-india/">Unemployment in India</a></p>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
            <item turbo="true">
            <title>Industrial Policy Of 1991 &#8211; Industrial Development in India</title>
        <link>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/04/industrial-policy/</link>
        <turbo:topic>Industrial Policy Of 1991 &#8211; Industrial Development in India</turbo:topic>
        <turbo:source>https://www.allexamnotes.com/2016/04/industrial-policy/</turbo:source>
                        <turbo:content><![CDATA[
                <header>
                        <h1>Industrial Policy Of 1991 &#8211; Industrial Development in India</h1>
                    </header>
                                <h2>INDUSTRIAL POLICY, 1991</h2>
<figure><img src="http://www.allexamnotes.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Kurien-202x300.jpg" /><figcaption>Professor P. J. Kurien of Vennikulam, Kerala, is a political and social worker, teacher and educationist. He known for Industrial Policy, 1991.</figcaption></figure>
<p>In order to accelerate <a href="http://www.allexamnotes.com/2017/01/industrial-development/">Industrial Development in India</a>, and in accordance with the changing circumstances, various industrial policies were declared in the years 1948, 1956, 1977, 1980 and 1985, but in spite of all efforts, the pace and as well as the level of Industrial Development in India, could not reached according to its need. Therefore, in order to lift unnecessary restrictions on Industries, under the licensing policy, and to increase their efficiency, development and technological level, in order to make Indian goods usable in the competitive global market, on 24th July, 1991, in Lok-Sabha the Minister of States for industries, Mr. P. J. Kurian declared the <strong>Industrial Policy, 1991.</strong></p>
<p><!--more--></p>
<h3>OBJECTIVES OF NEW INDUSTRIAL POLICY, 1991</h3>
<ol>
<li>To liberalise the economy</li>
<li>To increase employment opportunities</li>
<li>To encourage foreign assistance and co-partnership</li>
<li>To make the Public Sector more competitive</li>
<li>To increase the production and productivity, give encouragement to industries</li>
<li>To liberate the economy from various government restrictions</li>
<li>Industrial development of backward areas</li>
<li>To give liberty to private sector to work independently</li>
<li>To make development for modem competitive economy</li>
<li>To give encouragement for expansion of production capacity</li>
<li>To increase exports and liberalize (facilitate) imports.</li>
</ol>
<h2>SALIENT FEATURES OF NEW INDUSTRIAL POLICY, 1991</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<h4>Liberalized Industrial Licensing Policy</h4>
<p>Under this policy, with the exception of 18 industries, licensing system has been removed for all other industries. Some of those 18 industries, where the licensing system is still mandatory are; Army and Defence, Forest Conservation, Industries engaged in manufacturing goods which are harmful to the Environment and industries, which are manufacturing luxury goods, for the affluent (very rich) class, etc.</li>
<li>
<h4>Localisation Policy</h4>
<p>Those industries which are situated in cities, where the population is less than 1 million, industrial permission from the government, to start any industry is not required. In cities having population of more than 1 million, with the exception of electronics and other pollution free industries, all industrial units may be 25 kilo meters away from the city’s boundary.</li>
<li>
<h4>Foreign Investment</h4>
<p>Provision has been made to invest up to 51 percent by foreign investors in the equity shares of Indian Companies. Earlier, this limit was limited up to 40% only. This will increase the flow of foreign capital into India and make possible technical exchange from developed countries.</li>
<li>
<h4>Workers’ Participation in Management</h4>
<p>Under this industrial policy, emphasis has been laid on safeguarding the workers’ interest. Provision has been made for workers’ participation in management, in order to manage sick units, provision has been made to form co-operative societies of workers, to run them.</li>
<li>
<h4>Role of Public Sector</h4>
<p>Those public sector undertakings which are not doing well at present, but in which there are enough chances of improvement, shall be re-constituted. Public sector undertakings, which are facing constant financial crisis, shall be kept under observation by ‘Board of Industrial and Financial Reconstruction’ or by any other institution, which is fixed by the government.</li>
<li>
<h4>Change in the MRTP Act</h4>
<p>In the industrial policy 1991, major changes have been made in the <em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Monopolistic and Restrictive Trade Practice Act</span></em>. Companies having investment of Rs. 100 crores, will not be required to take prior Government permission, for opening new subdivisions, or to expand the present industry or for amalgamation of companies. This industrial policy has also eliminated the investment limit, which was fixed by MRTP Act.</li>
<li>
<h4>Creation of Productive Capacity</h4>
<p>In order to increase the productive capacity of new industries, all administrative controls have been removed. Industrialists will only have to inform the government of opening of new units or increasing their production capacity.</li>
<li>
<h4>Promotion of Industries in Rural Areas</h4>
<p>In order to remove the regional imbalances, under this industrial policy, various provisions have been made to encourage industries in rural areas.</li>
<li>
<h4>Foreign Technology</h4>
<p>No prior permission from government will be required in importing foreign technology, up to the limit of One Crore rupees. Indian companies, will be free to negotiate their terms and conditions, with their foreign collaborators, in matters of technology transfers (exchange of ‘technical know-how).</li>
<li>
<h4>Reservation of Small Scale Industries</h4>
<p>This policy has stated that the government shall keep giving assistance to small scale industries. The limit for small scale industries has been reduced from Rs 3 Crores to Rs. 1 Crore, since 24 December, 1999.</li>
</ol>
<h3>EVALUATION OF INDUSTRIAL POLICY, 1991</h3>
<p><em>“Industrial Policy 1991”</em> is also known as <em><strong>“Open Industrial Policy”</strong></em>, because it contains several revolutionary schemes and plans. If, we make an analytical study of the special features of Industrial Policy 1991, it becomes clear that several fundamental changes have been, made, in this policy.</p>
<ol>
<li>Liberalization of industrial licensing system</li>
<li>Welcoming of foreign capital</li>
<li>Facility of Import of Technical Know-how</li>
<li>Exemption to industrial structure from several unnecessary government controls</li>
<li>Aiming to make Indian industries more competitive at national and international level</li>
<li>Safeguarding the interest of workers, etc.</li>
</ol>                                                ]]></turbo:content>
            </item>
</channel>
</rss>
